Hello and welcome everyone to the course Learning Regular Expressions.
My name is Ellen Adams, I'm with O'Reilly Media, and
I'll be your facilitator for today's course.
Today, we welcome our instructor, James Lee.
Excuse.
Me in the early 1990s, James Lee installed Red Hat
on an unused piece of hardware he found in the
closet and he hasn't looked back since.
James.
He's assuming both personally and professionally and is particularly happy
that over his career in technology, he's never had to
use Windows.
You can read more in his bio and bio vision
and widget.
Ray, I will turn the program over to your structure
in just a moment.
But first I have to go over a few housekeeping
items up.
You get the most out of today's course.
At the top of your screen, there are a series
of options for interactions.
We'll primarily be using the Q&A and group chat.
They are open at the bottom of your screen and
you can post your questions and comments for James there.
These are resizable movable, so feel free to move them
around to get the most out of your desktop space.
And for those of you who are subject to regulated
status, the chat feature should not be used.
Bodies may include customers, vendors, or competitors of you or
your employer.
If you choose to take advantage of the right features
available in this course, and we hope that you will,
you're responsible for any information you choose to share.
We are recording the course and we'll have it ready
within 24 hours after the conclusion of the course.
We will notify you that e-mail soon.
The recording is available.
We also for it to remind your e-mail use the
course page link.
The recording be listed on the course page once it's
ready.
It's also same page you use in today's course.
The recording be listed on that page 24 hours after
we conclude.
There is a course feedback surveys located at the top
of your tray in the more menu button.
The second one before logging off towards your thoughts about
the course just attended.
We value your feedback and finding stream useful and viable,
and I'll dial for the delay.
I'd like to turn the program over to Shuck there.
Please welcome James Lee.
Thank you, Ellen.
Hello, everyone.
Welcome.
Good morning, good afternoon, good evening.
Wherever you are in the world.
Today we're going to talk about regular expressions.
I am very happy to be here to do this.
This is a topic that's very interesting to me and
I really like talking about it.
So welcome.
Couple things before we get started.
I do a lot of examples.
So I'm going to use this screen share quite a
bit.
And what ends up happening is I kind of go
back and forth between the screen share and the slides
and the back to the screen share back to the
slides.
I'll try to remind everyone kind of where I am
as I'm moving back and forth, but just be aware
that we, you know, there's going to be a lot
of demos shown here.
The second thing I wanted to mention is there's two
ways to ask questions.
There's the Q&A widget, which if you send a message,
I'll receive.
And then there's the attendee chat, the the participant chat
where you all can send messages and read each other's
messages.
And I monitor that throughout the course.
So as I'm talking, I kind of keep my eye
on that chat widget.
And if you put any questions in there, chances are
I'll see them and maybe be able to answer them
right away.
The other advantage of using that feature is you can
answer each other's questions.
So if someone knows the answer, feel free to drop
it in there.
But I'll, I'll eventually get to all the questions as
we go along.
And I do welcome the questions, so please feel free
to ask them.
And that's, I think that's all I need to tell
you to begin.
So let's start, shall we?
So learning regular expressions is what we're going to talk
about.
And by the way, I'm starting on the slides here.
So why, why should you be here in this class?
You're learning regular expressions because you need tools to locate,
parse, and replace text.
That's really the What regex's do powerfully is locate Parson,
replace texts.
I'm gonna pause for a second.
I just got a message about problems on the platform
trying to connect Ellen.
If if you're around someone's having trouble connecting.
So I'm not just I'm not really sure what I
can do, but Ellen's around to help.
So anyway, that's that's why we need Reg X's.
Another reason you're in this class is because you want
to be able to search and replace text to solve
day-to-day problems from simple problems to complex problems.
I use Reg X's daily.
There's as I work.
So when I'm working, I'm using Reg X's for various
things, searching code base or parsing a file or whatever.
So I use it all the time.
And you also may want to learn a text processing
tool that's used in many programming languages.
So regex's are part of most modern programming languages.
Now, to be in this class, you don't need to
know how to write code, but if you do know
how to write code, we're going to, at the end
of the class, we're going to look at some examples
in Python And JavaScript to parse to process text.
So that might be useful to you.
Again, you don't need to be a programmer to be
in the class, but if you are, we'll cover that
at the very end.
All right, so when we're done, hopefully you will understand
what Reg X's are, why they're used, the syntax and
rules of regular expressions, how to read and write them,
and how they're processed.
So that's my hope.
You'll also be able to use different tools like Grap,
eagrep said knock that use regular expressions.
You'll be able to read and more importantly, write Reg
XS, test and validate them and then again use them
in programming languages.
Although you don't need to be a programmer to be
in the class, all right, You should know and have
access to the of course files.
I think there is a zip file that should be
downloadable by you that has all the examples and things
that I'm going to be talking about.
And also know the basics of a shell and basic
shell commands.
If you're going to try things, look on your local
machine.
So again, I'll be doing a lot of demos, so
if you want to follow along, you need to know
basic shell commands.
I'm going to be working in Linux.
So the screen share I have here is a Linux
distribution.
It's Ubuntu.
I like this distribution mainly because it has all the
tools that we need for the class, and it's also
free, so that's good.
So let's just jump right into a demo.
Start with our demo.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
switch back to I'm going to switch over to the
screen share.
Now when I downloaded the zip file onto this Linux
machine here and unzipped it, I've got all these different
directories here that's in the zip file.
And each of these directories is contains examples and test
files and so on for the particular topic that we're
talking about.
So right now we're talking about the basic stuff.
So if I go into the basic directory here, there's
a couple files here it's just one file.
It's not not a whole lot in here.
We'll have some more stuff later.
But the first example I want to demonstrate is A1
very common use of Reg XS.
And that use is let I want to find some
text in a file.
And the way in the Linux world, the Unix world
to find text in a file is the grep command.
We're going to talk more about grep in a little
while.
But what grep does is it takes the first argument,
in this case express, and treats that as a regular
expression.
And we're going to talk more about what you know,
the rules of Reg XS.
But for now I can say this.
This regular expression means find in this in whatever I'm
searching and find an E followed by an X followed
by AP followed by an R followed by an E
followed by an S followed by an S So it's
all in a row, all lowercase in somewhere.
And the next argument is the somewhere.
So where am I going to look?
I'm going to look in user share dict words are
not my machine here.
This is a Dictionary of words and it's just one
word per line.
So what grep is going to do is find all
the lines that have this Reg X that match this
Reg X which is an E followed by an X
and so on.
So when I hit return we can see the result
here.
So these are all the lines that have EXPRESS.
Now, one thing I want to point out is that
most of the lines have the lines starting with express.
But here's a line down here where express is in
the middle of the line.
So by default, The Reg X will match anywhere in
the string.
Doesn't have to be at the beginning or the end
necessarily, or matches anywhere.
This is by default.
And this Ubuntu distribution highlights what matches in red, which
is kind of nice to read because you can clearly
see what part of the string matches.
It gets a little confusing later and I'll mention why
later, but you can see the results.
So what?
What's the common use of Reg X's locating text in
a file?
Now another common use of Reg X is is to
find a file somewhere in the file system that has
that matches some Reg X.
So I'm just going to clear my screen and show
this example.
So it's find is the command that finds files in
Linux in the Unix world.
Now, one note about find.
Find is a very complex feature rich command that helps
us locate files.
So there's all different options that you have to find.
So well, I'm just going to use a couple here,
but just know that there's a whole bunch of options,
a way to find files.
But here basically the the way to find is follows
this which is the find command followed by a directory
somewhere and I'm going to provide this directory now.
This is the mock commands documentation in this is a
directory in which there are files that are text files
basically.
And then I want to so it's going to basically
find all the files that are in this directory.
And then I'm going to say, OK, now execute this
command which is going to be the grep command and
grep minus H means show the file's name.
That's what the minus H means.
And then the regular expression here is regular.
There we go.
It spells sometimes.
And then I have to provide open close curly which
is the file that I'm finding.
So as I'm finding the file, its name is substituted
in this open close curly brace.
Kind of confusing, but that's how it works.
And then I need to terminate the grep which I
do with a back slash semi colon.
And then the problem with this command is it's going
to throw a lot of errors to standard error output.
I'm not interested in the errors.
I just want to see which files match this haves
text somewhere.
I should say I want to find the files that
have this regular somewhere in it.
So I'm going to take all of the standard error
output, which in the Unix world is known as two
greater than and two and then greater than means right
at 2:00.
And then this file dev null, which is a special
file in the Unix world, which basically anything you write
to it just gets discarded.
So when I run this, you can see, let me
expand this window a bit.
If I can do this, hang on one SEC.
OK, that's better.
So you can see the file name in which regular
is found.
And then the line that regular is has regular in
it.
You can see each of these lines has the text
regular so on OK, so that's what find does locate
a file that has this text in it.
OK in the in the last thing so we've able
to find text in a file.
Now we've able to find a file that has this
text.
The last example I'm going to show is a quick
demo is changing the contents of a file.
So that's where our words dot text is going to
come into play here.
So this is a very simple file.
It's got one word per line and you can see
it's the English text of the digits 0 through 9.
So what I want to do is I want to
use a regex to modify this file by substituting.
Now I can't use grep to do a substitution, but
I can use another Unix tool called said.
Said is stands for stream editor and it's a really
useful tool to do stream editor stuff, including substituting text.
And I'm going to provide this minus I option, which
means I'm going to do an inline substitution.
So this is actually going to modify the file that
it's working on.
OK, so then the next bit is a single quote,
single or double quoted string that looks something like this.
And I'll talk about what this means in a SEC
2nd and then the file itself.
So here's what set is going to do.
It's going to do an inline substitution means it's going
to change the file which is words dot TXT and
it's going to substitute and this slash here the limits,
which means begins and ends The Reg X and the
regular expression here is 0.
Now obviously that's AZ followed by E followed by R
followed by O, which matches only one line right here.
And then it's going to substitute it with the text
uppercase 0.
And you can see that's also within the delimiters here.
So if I run this, it won't be any standard
out, but if I can't words that text, we can
see that zero is uppercase.
Very nice.
Now I'm going to basically change it back because I
want it to be the original.
So I'm just going to substitute uppercase 0 with lowercase
0 and count it out.
Now it comes, it's converted back to lowercase.
OK, so WZ asks what is S in the beginning?
Good question.
This S right here me is a substitution command.
So said there's a lot of things.
It matches text, it prints stuff, it does a whole
bunch of stream editor type things.
You know, when you edit a file, it's there's a
lot of edit options that you can do.
And the S command or S operator here does string
substitutions.
We're basically saying substitute whatever matches this Reg X with
this text.
So anything that matches 0 uppercase will be substituted.
So that's what S means is substitute.
Good question.
OK, that's it for the quick demo.
So I'm going to go back to the slides.
Jump ahead a few pages because I just covered these.
All right, so let's talk about a little bit more
about the class here.
A lot of different, a lot of students attend this
class with different experience levels with Reg XS.
For instance, some folks come to the class and they
have absolutely no regular expression experience.
And for those that identify with that, welcome.
This is perfect class for you.
Then there's some classes, there's some students who come to
the class with a bit of regular expression knowledge and
some with quite a bit.
So what I like to do is I like to
say all of us are going to be on this
spectrum right here.
Some of us are on the left, which are new
to Reg XS, and some of us know everything.
Actually, nobody knows everything about Reg XS, but some of
us know more than others.
So we locate ourselves somewhere on this continuum here.
And the purpose of this class is to move, is
for everyone to move to the right.
That's it.
So if you're new to Reg X's, just know you're
going to move to the right.
And if you know a lot about Reg X's, you're
still going to move to the right.
So because we're going to talk about basic features, and
then towards the end of the class, very advanced features.
So those of us who are new to Reg X's,
the stuff at the beginning of the class is going
to move at a good pace.
And then when we get to the advanced stuff, it's
probably going to feel like we're moving too fast.
And those of us who know more Reg XS will
say, well, the stuff in the beginning is a little
slow, but then then the later stuff is going to
be just right.
So just place yourself on this spectrum here at this
continuum and we'll all try to move to the right.
All right, So a lot of really great books on
Reg XS.
I want to these are really good O'Reilly books here.
I want to recommend mastering regular expressions.
This is one of the best technical books I've ever
read about any topic really, and so I highly recommend
that book.
So check it out.
All right, the format is going to be talk, exercise
and break.
We haven't taken a break yet, but we've done the
other two things at least I've shown some examples, I
should say.
And then the exercise solutions are at the back of
this PDF.
So if you get stuck or you want to compare
your answers, feel free to flip to the back and
you'll find the solutions.
All right, so let's start talking more about an introduction
to regular expressions.
So we'll talk about what are they, why are they
important?
Talk more about grep and then look at some online
tools and then make sure we've answered all the questions.
So regular expressions are also known as Reg XS.
I tend to say Reg XS because it's easier to
say the sequence of characters describing a search pattern.
So that's what it is.
So what we're dealing with your search patterns and the
patterns contain characters that mean certain things.
We'll talk about what those characters mean as we go
along.
It's used to search text and two things we can
do when we found found the text is either match
it.
Which means it either matches or it doesn't.
Or substitute, which we saw a moment ago, which takes
whatever matches The Reg X and substitutes it with the
other word of the other text.
Now one note about these examples.
Right here you see those slash characters like the slash
before the the S and sum and the slash after
the X and then the slashes within the S I'm
going to use the slashes here simply to denote the
beginning and end of the regular expression so we can
read The Reg XS make sure we know when they
start, when they end.
Those slashes are typically not needed, especially when we're using
grap.
Grap they are needed and said they are needed in
programming languages usually, but in grap we don't need them.
So the.
So I just want to say that the slashes are
used mainly to delimit or denote the beginning and end
of The Reg X.
So we'll see that in examples as we go forward.
We can also we can search for text in files
with the grep command.
We saw what grep does is it matches its first
argument which is in this case hello with a capital
H in the argument which is the file.
So it looks in every line of file dot TXT.
If that line matches the regex which is capital H
followed by lower E, lower L, lower L, lower O
it prints the line out.
Now that this I want to emphasize that regex matching
is case sensitive.
So the case matters here.
This grep command greps for the that regex hello in
all the files in the current directory.
And you can also replace text in the file which
we saw with the said command earlier.
So this is going to substitute hello with goodbye.
Now the big the only difference really in this example
than the one we saw earlier is this.
This G kind of at the end of the substitute
command to the right of that last slash.
That G means global substitution because by default the substitute
will only substitute the first occurrence of hello with goodbye.
The G means substitute all occurrences of hello with goodbye.
We can also search and replace text in a directory
of files.
I am kind of stuck.
Hold on one second.
I'll.
Oh I see why.
OK, here we go.
Grep can also regex's are also used in other Linux
utilities like said, awk and find.
So we've seen grep, we've seen find and we've seen
said.
So if we have time, we'll talk about awk as
well.
Well, I think I dropped my screen share, so let
me share my screen again.
All right, let's see if that comes.
There we go.
OK, so here's what I hear a lot.
I'm seeing some chats come in here, so I think
stuff froze for a moment.
So let me just go through the chat here.
Someone indicated that the screen was freezing.
OK, WCZ says S&G are used in programming languages as
well or in grepfine only.
This is a great question.
So first of all, the G option is not OK.
The S&G option are kind of used in programming languages
but are typically used with a different feature.
What does that mean?
So instead, the S operator does substitutions.
In a programming language, it's typically a method or function
that you call to do the text substitution.
So the substitution is done with with a function instead
and that so that we'll see that when we get
to the programming languages later.
And the same with the G.
So the G is usually like a function argument or
something.
But there are some programming languages that use similar syntax
is what we've seen.
So I guess the this is a long winded way
of saying this.
The substitution and the global substitution are supported in programming
languages, but typically it's a different syntactical look to it.
Does that make sense?
All right, and I see a note here to one
of those students.
Please try refreshing your browser.
This is something that I've known would recommend.
If anyone's screen freezes or whatever, just refresh the browser.
That typically takes care of it.
OK, so back to this slide.
Here's something I hear all the time.
Yeah, but regular expressions are complicated.
And if we look at these regular, six regular expressions
here, we look at them and we go, what is
that?
I don't understand anything that's going on there.
In the end, this statement regular expressions are complicated is
absolutely correct.
There's no, there's no question about the regular expressions can
become complicated the more features that we use.
Now here's the good news.
Every example here is an example with features that we're
going to talk about in this class.
So my hope is by the end of the class,
you'll at least be able to somewhat understand what's going
on here, even though these are very, very complex Reg
XS.
But here's the thing about complicated things.
Powerful tools are complex.
That's just all there is to it.
With Reg XS, we can do a lot.
But here's the thing with Reg XS, we can do
a lot with a little.
And the more we know, the more we can do.
I was as an analogy, I always think back to
when my kids were young and just beginning to talk.
They just knew a few words.
But I'm going to tell you they were able to
get their point across.
Even though they only knew knew a little English.
They could make the point what they wanted, what etcetera.
And then the more English they learned, the more they
could communicate.
But the key is they could do a lot with
a little, and that's same with regular expressions.
And Reg X's are kind of like are basically a
language.
And again, you can say a lot with the littles.
And the purpose of this class is to learn enough
so that these complicated Reg X's become more understandable.
All right, now there's six basic, there's six different dialects
of Reg X's in the first, I should say major
dialects.
The first of the dialects is what we call BRE,
which is base regular expressions.
And this is what the grep command supports.
These were the very first features, a feature this this
feature set was in the early days of regular expressions,
way back when regex's were created.
And yeah, so they're basic features.
And then it was kind of, as things were evolving,
realize that we need another rule set, so the extended
regular expression rule set was created.
It is basically what base is, plus a whole bunch
of new features.
There's also a dialect for Emacs.
There's a dialect for them and then there's PCREPCRE is
an acronym that stands for Pearl compatible regular Expressions.
And this PCR is the most the feature rich dialect
of Reg XS.
And the good news is we can use this with
GRE minus capital P and because it's the feature rich
set and we're going to use a lot of these
features that are only available in PCRE, we're going to
use the PCRE dialect.
So that means going forward, most of our examples using
GRAP will be grap minus cap P, so that we're
going to do that.
There's also a Pearl 6 version, which is specifically for
the Pearl, the version six of the Pearl programming languages
language, excuse me.
So we're going to basically work with PCRE.
Now, the good news is is Python And JavaScript both
support PCRE.
So when we get to that later in the class,
we'll be able to talk about that.
All right, so Rag X's are really like another language.
The roots are in mathematics and computer science theory and
so rec akasis can kind of be considered code kind
use this very kind of loosely a little bit because
it's not code, but it kind of sense that it's
a little bit like code.
So there are statements, loops and subroutines.
Now notice the statements and the loops and subroutines are
quoted and the quotes are basically to say there's not
really statements, but you can think of them as statements,
and there's not really loops, but you can, and so
on.
OK, so that means we can apply code design skills
if we have them.
And regex is running a specialized virtual machine, and we'll
see how that works later.
So let's talk more about grep.
So common question is what does grep, where did the
name grep come from?
Does it, is it an acronym?
Does it stand for that?
What is it?
What it is is a command that was used in
the very first Unix editor.
That editor was called Ed, and in Ed you could
run a command which looked like this.
You type G, that means global for every line in
this file.
That's what the G means.
Then you say slash that begins and ends The Reg
X, and then you got the regular expression in there.
I'll shorten that to RE a regular expression and then
a close slash and then P to print.
So this means this for every line in the file,
if the line matches this regular expression, print it out.
And that's exactly what grep does.
Looks at every line in the file.
If the line matches The Reg X, the line gets
printed.
So that's where the name grep comes from.
So the grep command without any arguments, he uses the
BRE.
That's the base regular expression dialect.
That's the one with the fewest features.
E grap which is equivalent to grap minus cap E
is equivalent is uses the extended regular expression dialect, which
is like the base but with more features.
And then grap minus capital P in most Linux's uses
PCRE.
That's the Pearl compatible regular expression, which is the most
feature rich dialect and we're going to be using that
in this class.
And just a note again, PCRE is supported by JavaScript
and Python.
So when we get to that, at the end of
the class, you'll see, and there's a link there to
a CHEAT SHEET which basically shows the differences between BREERE
and PCRE.
All right, so let's jump to some more examples.
I'm going to go back to my screen share now.
All right, so here we are in the screen share.
Now we saw an example before using grep.
I'm just typing this in.
So this again, this grep OK SA askswhichdoes.net use OK,
this is a good question.
I'm not 100% on this answer because I'm I'm assuming
which dialectdoes.net use I I'm not a.net expert, I've really
never programmed in it, but here's what I'm going to
go out on a limb and say.
I'm pretty sure this is true.
It supports ERE, maybe out sort of out-of-the-box with no
libraries or anything, but if you install a particular library,
it will support PCRE because that is the case for
most programming languages.
Like for JavaScript, kind of the the normal distribution supports
ERE, but you can use a library to support PCRE.
Same for Python.
So I'm going to guess.net is probably the same.
So yeah, the good news is it will support regular
expressions.
Good question.
OK, back to the screen share here.
So the grep command again, it looks at every line
of this file.
If the line matches this regular expression, it prints it
out.
So let's see what lines get printed.
So here are all the lines in the dictionary that
have hello anywhere in the line.
You can see here it's at the end of the
line.
Here it's in the middle of the line, the entire
line and so on all right, so and again the
this command in this in the Ubuntu Linux will print
it out like in red here to show exactly what
part of the line matched.
OK AI thank you so much for pasting that message
from Microsoft and is compatible with Pearl five regular expressions,
which is Pearl PCRE.
So thank you very much for that.
OK, now about some back to the screen share here.
Something about the grip is as the regular expression gets
more complicated, it becomes more necessary for it to be
quoted.
And the quotes here are just kind of providing the
beginning and end of the argument on the command line.
Here in Linux, you can see it provides the same
result in this example.
I don't need it, but as the examples get more
complicated, I'm going to need it.
So I should probably just start using the quotes.
Now.
Let's try this.
I'm going to use the vertical bar.
Now we don't know what the vertical bar is, but
very briefly, we'll talk about more detail later.
The vertical bar means either or, so one or the
other.
So this grep command is hopefully going to look in
the dictionary and print out lines that either match hello
or match goodbye.
So one or the other.
Now this doesn't work because the grep command is not
too friendly because I have to escape that vertical bar.
You see that?
So to escape the vertical bar I have to proceed
it with this back slash character and now I get
hello or goodbye.
So this is grepping for hello or goodbye in the
dictionary and you can see the lines that match either
hello or goodbye.
Now the reason that this is the back slash vertical
bar is necessary is because grep is base regular expressions
BRE.
But I can use ERE by doing the E grep,
and then I don't need to escape.
And by the way, egrep is the same as grep
minus cap E, So egrep grep minus cap E, same
thing.
This is the extended regular expressions, which means I one
of the features I don't have to escape that slash
that, yeah, that vertical bar.
Excuse me.
So that's good.
All right, so let's go to the next grep example.
By default, grep is case sensitive.
So if I do this, I'm grepping for lower a
followed by lower U, followed by lower S and so
on.
We can see there's just a few of those.
But if I use grep minus I, the I means
do a case insensitive.
That means ignoring case, and you can see all the
lines that have an A followed by U followed by
S followed by T followed by R In any case,
see all those other lines that get printed out?
So the minus I is useful to do a case
in sensitive match.
Now let's say I have a file called regex's dot
TXT.
I'm just going to create it real quick here and
it's going to have this content.
All right, So just three lines and these three lines
are going to be 3 separate regular expressions.
So I've got the regular expression.
This is the first one, second one, third one.
I'm going to say this and then I'm going to
use this by saying grep minus F and then this
file in care about that.
OK in the dictionary file and notice it uses the
three regular expressions that are in that file and uses
them to search the dictionary and it prints all the
lines that match either of those rag XS in the
file.
OK question, is there a way to record all your
grep commands to a file as you use them?
There are I can do something like this at the
end of the class.
I don't know how many commands I'm going to have
by the end of the class, maybe 202,000 I don't
know.
And then I'll write those to a file and then
I'll say I'll make them available to y'all so we'll
do that at the end.
OK, so the last grep example here is let's look
at our file words dot TXT and then I'm going
to say grep NE in words dot TXT.
So what does this do?
This finds all the lines that contain an N followed
by an E, and you can see there's two lines
that have an N followed by an E Then the
question is, what if I want to show all the
lines that don't match in followed by east?
That is the minus V option.
So minus V will print all the lines that don't
match.
So that's the other 8 lines.
All right, so there's a bit more on grep.
I'm going to go back to my slides now and
jump ahead to the end of these examples.
So I've just shown all these examples, OK?
If you're working in the Windows world, yes, grep is
available for Windows.
You can follow that link there or a good search
of the Internet will help you as well.
Now if you're working in Mac OS, there is grep
that's distributed with the Mac OS, but it it only
supports BRE and ERE.
So if you want PCRE, what you do for this
class, there is a brew allows you to install a
library called grep.
And when you install that library with those command, those
brew commands there the improved grep, this is the grep
with PCRE is now known as G grep.
So G grep is now the grep with PCRE.
So that's if you're working in the window of the
OS world, Mac OS world that is.
And there's a lots of online tools that are available
to work with regular expressions and to test out your
regex's.
Before I show an example, let me just draw attention
to that last one, the regex crossword.
This is a really cool thing where you can kind
of quiz yourself with regular expressions, and it's a great
way to learn.
It's kind of a fun way to learn regexes.
But I'm going to go to theregexr.com as an example,
and I've got it right here on the screen share.
So what we have is some text.
Let me get rid of all this here.
We've got some text right here, and this is the
text we're going to search.
And then we've got the ability to type in a
regular expression up here.
So I'm going to type in A.
Now, when I type A, that regular expression means match
A anywhere, right?
So it shows all the parts of the text that
have that match A.
And then if I type R, these are all the
places that match AR.
So you can see there's three of them and if
I type EARE so we see the two places and
the text that have ARE.
Now the nice thing about it is down below it
shows what the regex means.
So it kind of converts the regular expression into English
and we can kind of understand it perhaps better.
So I encourage use of online tools to kind of
test out regex's.
It's also a really helpful learning tool, so you can
give that a try if you want.
All right, next slide is Q and AI.
Think I'm caught up with all the questions, so I'm
just going to go on to the next bit.
And that's basic syntax.
Now you probably notice we've been talking like 40 minutes.
I'm going to go a little bit longer and then
we'll do an exercise and take a break.
So you'll get a break in a little bit, so
just hang with me.
All right, let's talk about the basic syntax rules.
And this is kind of a summary of all the
things we're going to talk about here.
First, the basic regular expression rules.
So that normal, we're going to talk about normal characters
and the dot character.
We'll also talk about the beginning and end of the
line with the carrot and the dollar.
We'll discuss what the how the regex engine works and
discuss regex rule #1 and then we'll do an exercise,
which is a kind of a pencil to paper exercise
that you can try.
And then we'll take a also take a break there.
And then we'll look after the break.
We'll look at the solution and make sure I answer
all the questions.
OK, so we've talked about the basics really.
So most characters alphanumeric match themselves.
So here I'm gripping A in file dot text.
The A means match A anywhere in the string, so
A matches A.
So most alphanumeric characters just match themselves.
So if I have a grip ABC in file dot
text, that matches an A followed by AB followed by
AC anywhere in the string.
The thing is that those things have to be right
next to another because we're specifying A and then B
and then C, So it has to be A immediately
followed by B immediately followed by C, And here we're
grepping for AB12.
So that means matching A immediately followed by AB and
then followed by a one and then followed by A2
anywhere in the string.
So most characters simply match themselves.
There is an exception, the dot character.
The dot character means match any character except the new
line character.
So this stands in for any character at all except
for new line.
So this grep example says match A dot B in
file dot text.
That means match an A immediately followed by any character
except new line followed by B.
So if I have grep A dot B dot C,
that means match A immediately followed by anything except new
line followed by B followed by any character but new
line followed by C OK, And the final rules we'll
look at is carat in dollar.
So I've emphasized this a few times and that the
rule is this.
By default, Reg XS can match anywhere in the string.
However, sometimes we do want to match The Reg X
at the beginning of the string or at the end
of the string, and we do that with these two
special characters.
So the carrot, that's the thing that looks like it's
pointing up.
By the way, on my keyboard, that's a shift six.
That carrot character means match the beginning of the string,
and then the dollar character means match the end of
the string or right before new line at the end
of the string.
Case your line has a new line character at the
end.
So let's look at some examples here.
So here we're saying grep carrot ABC.
That means match the beginning of the string immediately followed
by A and then B and then C In other
words, match ABC at the beginning of the string.
So now we're bounding it, if you will, to the
beginning of the string.
ABC dollar means matching A followed by AB followed by
AC immediately followed by the end of the string.
So that matches ABC at the end of the string
or right before new line at the end of the
string.
And then if we use them both, this means match
the care.
ABC dollar means match begin the string followed by A
followed by B followed by C followed by the end
of the string.
So it simply matches ABC or ABC new line because
that dollar will match before the new line character.
All right, so quick summary here.
Most characters match themselves dot matches any character, but new
line character matches the beginning of the string.
Dollar matches the end of the string.
Now if we want to match one of these special
characters, it has to be escaped that back slash.
So that first grep command means matching A followed by
back slash dot means actually match the period character.
That's A followed by the period character followed by B
followed by the period character followed by C The next
example is carrot.
Match the beginning of the string followed by back slash.
Carrot is the actual carrot character, back slash dollar is
the actual dollar character, and then dollar is the end
of the string.
OK, WC says carat ABC ampersand.
OK, that should be carat ABC.
Dollar means match a line contains ABC only, right?
That is correct.
So it's carat ABC dollar sign.
All right, so let's look at this example.
I'm going to jump back over to the screen share
and just show the exam these quick examples here.
So again, here's words dot text.
The first example is grep, and again I'm using minus
P.
Why am I using minus P?
The minus cap P option to grep uses the PCRE
dialect.
That's the Pearl compatible regular expression dialect.
This is the most feature rich dialect and the one
we're going to use throughout the class.
So that's what that grep minus cap P means.
My rag X is simply in and then the file
words dot text.
This is going to match every line that contains an
N anywhere in it.
You can see there's three lines that contain N somewhere.
Now here is where the highlighting becomes a little confusing.
You see how the N here and the N here
is shown, both of them.
This is basically saying this rag X has the potential
to match either of these places in the line.
All right, Now if I change this Reg X to
be in followed by E, now we see 2 lines
that match.
Let's change this to simply R.
And this shows all the lines that match an R
character.
You can see those lines there.
All right, so let's try this carrot in.
This means match any lines that begin with the N
character.
You see there's only one that begins with N And
then we if we say R dollar, this means match
a line that ends with an R.
There we go.
4 is the only line that ends with an R.
And then if we search for a regex that doesn't
match anything, then nothing gets printed that makes sense.
OK, back to our slides.
We can kind of think this is just kind of,
but we can kind of think of regular expressions as
statements.
So let's look at this regex example here.
Now remember, the slash denotes the beginning of in the
end, this is only for you and I to be
able to kind of read what's on the slide here
and make sure we know exactly where it begins and
ends.
And the regex here is carrot ABC dollar.
We just saw this example.
That means match the beginning of the string followed by
A followed by B followed by C followed by the
end of the string.
So if we think about this, this is kind of
like a coding statement.
If A is at the beginning of the string and
then if B and then if C at the end
of the string then match.
Now this work is done in what we call the
regular expression state machine.
I like to think of this as a state machine.
I think it's easier to understand for me anyway.
So if we look at that regex carrot ABC dollar,
here's the state machine that it creates.
So we have we sort of begin the machine, the
state on the left and we go into the state
begin the string.
So if we're at the beginning of the string that
is satisfied, then if the next character is a match
the a, then if the next, we move to that
state.
Then if the next character is B, we move to
that state.
Next character C we move to that state and we
determine if it's at the end of the string.
If that's the case, then we match.
And the regex engine is going to do this for
us to try to match for us.
So let's talk about this, the basics of this engine.
The first I want to the first thing before we
talk about this is to say this to you make
this comment about the engine.
The engine is going to try everything it can to
match the rag X.
It's going to do everything possible in order to match,
which means it's going to try all possible options, alternatives.
Here's how it does so in the in the engine.
So it starts at the left of the rag X,
and it starts at the left of the string.
It's going to try all possible paths, and then as
it's going through, it's going to backtrack as little as
possible.
We're going to talk more on this later.
If there's a match, then yeah, success, we're done.
If there's not a match, in other words, if there's
a failure touch, we'll move along 1 character in the
string, start over at the beginning of the rec Reg
X and try all possible paths again.
And we're going to continue to do that.
Either match or move along, match, move or move along,
match or move along.
Now, if we fail starting at every character, so we've
moved along through all the characters, then we fail to
match.
So the engine is going to do all this work
for you, to do everything it can to match.
I think the best way to understand this these basics
is with an example.
All right and I'm going to talk about this by
saying what is regex rule #1 Regex rule #1 the
earliest match wins.
WZ says some languages start from right to left, not
left to right.
How to solve this issue?
Wow, this is a great question.
I don't, I don't have a a very high confidence
in this answer.
I'm going to give what I suspect is the answer
and then during the break, I will try to find
the answer for you.
I'm just making a note to do that when we're
in our break.
Here's what I think.
I think it'd be if the language is right to
left, that it's going to search from right to left
through the text.
Now the question is The Reg X, does it go
left to right, right to left?
I'm not 100% sure on that, but I'm going to,
I'm going to speculate that if the language is a
right to left, that's the direction it's going to search.
But I will find that out for you anyway.
Great question.
OK, so the earliest match is going to win.
So going back to English here, we're going to, we're
going to basically do the following when we're searching.
So we have a string here and that is we're
going to start from the left.
So we have a string, a fundamental idea of rag
X's.
They are fun.
So hopefully you'll agree with me with that sentiment at
the end of the class.
And then we have a rag X here, which is
denoted by the delimiters.
Again, the delimiters are not necessary and grap or whatever.
It's just helping us read where it begins and ends.
And The Reg X is an F followed by U
followed by N.
Now if we look in this string, we see there's
two places in the string where FUN exists, right at
the beginning of the fundamental, the word fundamental, and then
at the end of the string, the word fun.
So the question is what part is going to match?
And the answer is the first occurrence matches.
So what's Reg X?
Rule number one, The first occurrence will match.
All right, so let's let's see how this actually works.
Let's say we have the string ABCDEFG and the regex
ABC.
Question is, does ABC match ABCDEFG?
The answer is, of course it does.
You and I can look at that and say, yeah,
it's going to match.
How?
That's because we have really smart brains and we can
just look at things and see it.
But the regex engine is not smart like us.
It's an engine that will determine this match, but it
takes some work, so let's see how it works.
So again, start at the left of the string left
of the regex.
So the next thing in the regex is the character
A is the next character in the string in a
yes match.
All right, so The Reg X says the next character
needs to be AB is the next character in the
string AB yes match.
And then The Reg X says the next character must
be AC is the next character AC yes match?
So we match the string.
All right, let's look at this example.
Here we have a BABCDEFG.
Does that match ABC?
You and I look at that string and say, sure,
there's ABC somewhere in that string.
They followed by B followed by C But again, The
Reg X engine can't just look at it and determine,
so it has to do some work.
So it starts at the left of the string, left
of The Reg X.
What's the next character we're looking for?
an A is the next character an A?
Yes, match is the next character AB.
Yes, match is the next character AC.
No, the next character is not AC.
So what happens is it's going to fail here.
So what happens is is we begin back at the
beginning of the regular expression and move along 1 character
in the string.
So now we're looking for the character A is the
next character in a NO, the next character is AB.
So again, start back at the beginning of the regex,
move along 1 character in the string.
Now it's the next character in A, yes.
Then AB, then AC match.
See that?
So I had to do a little bit more work,
but eventually got there to match our regex.
All right, so let's look at this example.
A/B, A/B, A/B.
So does A/B, A/B, A/B match ABC?
No.
You and I look at this and say there's no
way this is going to match.
But again, we have smart brains, we can see this.
The regex engine has to do work.
So here's the work.
Start at the left of the string, left of the
regex looking for an A which matches looking for AB
which matches looking for AC Fail.
So we start at the beginning of the regex.
The next character in the string is the next character
in a no.
So move along to the next character in the string.
Is the next character an A?
Yes.
Is the next character AB?
Yes.
Is the next character AC?
No.
So start at the beginning of The Reg X and
the next character in the string which is not an
A.
So the next character in the string which is an
A.
Then we match the B and then there's no C
so we fail.
So notice the engine is trying every possible combination to
try to match for you and it eventually finds the
OK, let's do an exercise.
So this is meant to be kind of pencil of
paper if you will.
Or you can verify it with the grep command.
It's up to you.
So we've got these words in words dot text, which
we're familiar with by now.
And over here we have 6 Reg XS, The Reg
XT, The Reg X dot N dot, The Reg X,
carrot T, and so on.
What I want you to do is for each of
these Reg XS, determine which of the words on the
left are going to match.
So for #1, The Reg X is T So that
basically means any line that contains the letter T.
So which lines on the left contain the letter T
and then #2 and then so on through #6 And
then the second part of exercise one is to write
Reg XS.
So write a Reg X that matches a line with
E anywhere in the line that matches the line that
starts with E, that matches 4 character, that lines that
begin with F and then with E.
OK, so we've been talking quite a bit, so I'm
going to give you a bit of time here.
I'm going to give you let's take 15 minutes.
I'm gonna suggest if I'm gonna start a 15 minute
timer here and in 15 minutes there we go.
Cuz it'll take you about maybe no more than 10
minutes to do the exercise and then take a little
bit of a break.
And then in 15 minutes we'll get back together and
show the solutions to exercise 1.
So I'll, I'll be back then.
By the way, I'm standing by to answer any questions
that are asked in the chat.
OK, everyone.
We have about one minute and then I'm going to
go through the solutions to exercise one.
OK everyone, welcome back.
So let's look at exercise one jump over here to
my screen share.
Remember this is our words dot TXT.
So the question is for #1 which words are going
to match AT simply T?
And we see these words 238.
So let's prove that because these are the only lines
that contain AT somewhere in the line 238.
All right, the next one is this Reg X.
Now this Reg X is dot, which means match any
character except new line followed by N followed by dot,
which is any character but new line.
So this is basically an end with a character to
the left and a character to the right.
And we see there's two lines that match that.
All right.
Next up is carrot T Carrot means match the beginning
of the line.
So this or the string and this means T at
the beginning.
So there are two lines that have T at the
beginning of the string, All right?
Next up is E dollar sign.
That means E at the end of the word.
So these are the lines with an E at the
end of the word into the line, I should say.
And so there's four, there's 4 lines of words dot
text with an E at the end.
Similarly, this is grepping for NE at the end of
the line into the string.
So there's two strings there within E at the end.
And then finally we've got this one.
So let's look at this as carat dot dot dot
dollar.
And So what this means is carat means begin the
string, Then we have three dots.
That's any character followed by except new line, followed by
any character except new line, followed by any character except
new line, and then dollar sign into the strings.
This is basically 3 character strings.
This only matches 3 character strings and you can see
there's 33 character strings in this file.
All right, do the next one which is match lines
with E anywhere in the line.
That's simply grep E by the way, I'm in Part
2 where we're writing regular expressions to do the following
E anywhere in the line.
It says match lines that start with E Well that's
carrot E, so one line starts with an E.
This is match 4 character lines that begin with F
in with E So I begin the string with an
F2, other characters, then E at the end of the
string.
All right, very good.
OK, two things.
First thing is WZ asked about languages that read right
to left.
I was.
I found an article on one language that reads right
to left.
I, I, I want to try to tailor the answer
to the language that you have questions about South WZ.
If you're comfortable sharing the language in the the group
chat, please do so.
Otherwise, send me AQ and a message which is private
to me and then I will attempt to find some
information about that regex is in that language.
That's number one.
Number two, someone asked for the the commands that I'm
typing in over here and I'm happy to share them
with you.
So what I'm going to do is create a text
file with the history of this class and I'm going
to put it in the the link that I am
pasting into the chat.
So remember that all all suggestion slash warning supplies that
goes to a private website.
But anyway, that file does not yet exist.
It will exist later today.
So I'll dump the history, put it in that file,
put it on online, and you'll have that again later
today.
It won't work right now.
OK, I think I've answered.
Oh, Arabic.
OK, I have a pretty decent article.
Let me just real quick Google this again and I'll
have it for you one minute.
So I'm just going to type this in here.
All right, so I found this article, pasting it in
the chat again, same suggestions apply.
This article looks pretty good for applying regular expressions to
Arabic.
I don't know Arabic, so I'm was reading through it
and it I could sort of understand and I think
this will help.
So check that out.
WZ if you have any other questions about it, please
ask.
OK, all the questions answered.
Let's go to character classes.
Now.
By the way, we talked a long time this that
first talk.
We won't do that again.
I won't give really long talks.
It'll be shorter talks, exercises and so on.
So the next topic is character classes.
So we're going to talk about the syntax of character
classes matching a character that's in a class and matching
a character that's not in a class.
We'll talk talk about POSIX classes, predefined classes.
Then we'll do an exercise.
All right, in a class.
What does that mean?
You want to match a character that exists a much
of amongst a group of characters.
For instance, let's say you want to match either an
A or AB or AC or AD or an E
The way to do that is to take that group,
put that within square brackets so see within the slashes.
Again, the slashes are just the delimiter so we can
read the regex.
The regex is open square bracket, ABCDE close square bracket.
And what that means is match one, only one character
that's either A or B or C or D or
E just one.
Now in these classes you can specify a range with
the dash.
So A-E is the same as ABCDE.
So that matches 1 character A through E.
So if I have A-Z, this matches one lowercase alpha.
Remember case sensitivity.
And then this slide shows this last example 0-9, which
is match 1 digit character.
So the square brackets match a class, and in the
class we get to choose one of those characters.
All right, so let's do an example real quick.
We have another file, so let me talk about that
for a moment.
So right now I am in the basic subdirectory here.
There's another subdirectory called classes.
So I'm just going to jump over there and cat
out the text dot text file.
And it's the same file here on the screen share
as you see on the slide over there.
So let's run through the examples that are on the
the next slide and I'll just do them here on
the screen share.
So I have grep minus cap P.
Just a reminder, grep minus cap P means Pearl compatible
regular expressions and I can do A-Z in text dot
text.
So that's going to find all the lines that match
this regex, which is 1 occurrence of A through Z.
Now again, it's kind of confusing here because it highlights
in red all the characters, excuse me, all the characters
that match lowercase A through Z, which is AT and
an E and an S and so on.
But we learned that regex rule #1 is this.
The first thing that matches is the thing that matches.
So this is going to match T here, TTOT and
so on.
So the first thing that matches is what is matched.
OK, next example is expand this a bit and match
A-Z.
That's one occurrence of an A through Z followed by
1 occurrence of a digit.
And here we have one occurrence of an A through
Z that's T followed by 1 occurrence of a digit.
So that's what matches there.
Now I'm going to add here in this example a
dash.
Now this means match A through Z or dash followed
by a digit.
And we can see down here now it's matching these
dashes.
OK, now I'm just going to suggest this is my
preference.
I'm about to say this is my preference.
The rule is if a dash is at the end
of the regex thing here, it means match the dash
character.
But the dash has a very important role in these
character classes.
So I'm kind of confused.
Is this dash right here a range?
Or is this dash the dash?
So what I like to do, this is just me,
is escape that dash character.
And this escape says to me as I read it,
oh, that matches the dash character.
In this case, dash is not used as the range.
It's actually the dash character.
Now you don't need it, but that's what I do.
OK, there's another file, a bunch of phone numbers, so
let's write some regex's to see them to clear my
screen.
Try this again.
There we go, it's a little bit better.
So I'm going to just start to match a phone
number.
So I'm going to say 0-9, 0-90-90-9 in phone numbers.
Now what this is going to do is it's going
to match a digit followed by a digit, followed by
a digit followed by a digit.
Now obviously it's going to match 4 digits in a
row, and every one of these lines has four digits
in a row, so it's going to match every line.
So this is kind of the beginning regular expression to
match a phone number.
And we're starting very simple here, or simple ish.
We'll get more complicated as we go along with these
phone numbers.
But let's look at another example, which is I'm going
to match.
Now this is going to be a little bit more
complicated example, so I'm going to wrap it in quotes
just so grep doesn't get confused with any spaces in
there.
And I'm going to match.
This example has 3 digits and then another 3 digits,
and between each 3 digits we have this class.
It's a space or a dash.
So this is going to match 3 digits space 3
digits or three digits dash 3 digits.
And you can see we've got 3 digits, dash 3
digit, space, 3 digit, space 3 digits, and so on.
So you can see the lines that match.
So this is kind of the beginning of a Reg
X that'll match all these phone numbers.
We'll get to it as we go along.
And the other thing you're going to note is that
The Reg X is now beginning to get a little
hard to read, and we're going to make this Reg
X more readable as we go along as well.
OK, back to the slides.
I'm going to jump ahead here.
All right, How about not in the class?
So if the if the square brackets, the first character
of the square brackets is a carrot, that means match
a character not in this class.
So this example says because of the square brackets and
then that carrot it says match one occurrence of a
character neither A nor B nor C nor D nor
E so any character except ABCDE.
And this is the same but using the dash for
a range.
So this example carrot A-C means match a non lowercase
non lower alpha character.
So anything but a lowercase alpha character and this one,
the carrot 0-9 means match one non digit character, any
character by the digit.
All right, so let's go back to the screen share
and I'll show these examples real quick.
All right, so I'm going to clear my screen over
here and we're going to do a grep minus cap
P and then it's carrot A-C in the text file.
So these are all the lines that contain a non
digit, excuse me, non lower alpha character.
And you can see the parts of the string that
match.
And I remember rule number one, first part of the
string wins.
So we know which character is actually matching, but it's
showing all the potential matches, if you will.
All right, so let's let's follow a non lower alpha
with the non digit.
So we have a non lower A1 followed by a
non digit dash.
Let's reverse those.
Let's match a non digit followed by a non lower
alpha and we see non digit followed by non lower
alpha T1 or E dash.
All right, back to the slides.
Jump ahead here.
OK, let's talk about POSIX character classes.
POSIX is a just very briefly, POSIX is basically was
an attempt to create a standard Unix.
It's called POSIX.
But in as a result, there were these character classes
that kind of came out of that effort and they
have a very strange syntax.
But here's what the syntax looks like.
So let's there are some classes, some groups of characters
that are very common, like lowercase alphas.
So we have the character class A-Z.
That's one occurrence of a lower alpha.
That A-Z can be replaced with open square colon, the
term lower colon close square.
Now this is really confusing because we have this double
open square, double close square business, but the outer squares
create the class.
The inner squares represent the character class, in this case
lower alphas.
So it's weird that there's two sets of square brackets,
but that's just the way it works.
So they're a bunch of POSIX character classes, including these.
We've got alnom, that's alphanumeric, that's lower alphas, upper alphas,
digits.
We've got alpha, which are all the lower and upper
alphas.
Lower is in there, upper, that's the uppercase alphas.
Notice the word.
So word are what are known as word characters.
Word characters are considered lower alphas, upper alphas, digits, under
score.
So a word character includes that under score there.
But anyway, these are all a subset of the POSIX
character classes available now.
Just a note about POSIX.
I almost never use POSIX classes, so in my day-to-day
I'll use another kind of shortened character class, which we'll
talk about in a moment.
But POSIX classes I typically don't use.
So if you want to use these, great.
Just just so you know, I don't typically.
All right, here's some examples.
Oh by the way, to negate include the carrot after
the first colon.
I know the syntax is weird here, but that carrot
means any non lower alphas for the lower carrot digit
means any non digit characters.
So this class, the outer square brackets says this is
a character class and then within the square brackets we
have A1 or A2 or a non digit.
So this matches any character that's either one or two
or any non digit character.
So basically it matches anything except zero and then three
through 9.
This matches the second one.
The outer squares means a character class.
Then we have ABC followed by non lowers alphas.
So this is either an A or AB or AC
or IN or any non lower alpha.
So essentially it matches that class.
Now I look at these again, they seem confusing.
They're kind of hard to work with, a little clunky.
This is why I normally don't use them.
So let's look at some examples here real quick.
These are going to really challenge my typing skills.
All right, so I'll grab minus cat P because there's
so many square brackets.
I think that is right.
So this this says match all any line that contains
a lower alpha character.
All those lines contain at least one lower alpha.
This one matches any line that contains a digit character.
And you can see the lines that contain digit characters.
And this one is non lower alphas, so match any
line that contains a non lower alpha character.
OK, so that's POSIX compliant.
I should say POSIX character classes, again I don't use
them much.
But back to the slides.
Generic character classes I use all the time, so these
I I very frequently use and these kind of satisfy
my requirements almost always when I'm dealing with character classes,
it's kind of standard character classes.
So notice they all have a back slash character followed
by an alpha like a lowercase D, uppercase D, lowercase
W, uppercase W and these stand in for some character
class.
So back slash lowercase D is the same as open
square 0 through 9 close square back slash uppercase D
is the same as open square carat 0 through 9
close which is non digit.
So back slash uppercase D is 1 occurrence of a
non digit character.
Back slash lowercase W is 1 occurrence of a word
character.
Again word characters are lower alphas, upper alphas, digits, under
score back slash uppercase W are non word characters.
So anything but a lower alpha, upper alpha digit or
under score back slash lowercase S these are space characters.
Space character is considered a space like the space bar,
a tab that's back slash T, new line, back slash
N carriage return, which are used in like Windows files
that's back slash R and then back slash F is
what's called a form feed.
And what is a form feed?
Way back in the day, if you printed a form
feed to a printer, it would go to the next
page.
Yeah, that's like ancient technology there.
But anyway, then you have non space characters or anything
but those characters.
You've also got horizontal and vertical white space.
I I rarely use those though.
So let's look at an example.
So back to my screen share here.
Let's look at this example.
I'm going back to this.
Remember this, this is grep.
I'm going to go ahead and put my quotes in
here just because I want to.
So this matches 4 digits.
Now first of all, it works great, but it's hard
to type and it's a bit hard, it gets a
bit hard to read.
But here's the thing.
Each of these can be replaced with a back slash
D like this.
Back slash D means one occurrence of a digit, exact
same result.
And I maintain this, it's much easier to read than
this and also much easier to type.
So once you learn that back slash D means one
occurrence of a digit, way easier.
So if we look, remember the other example where we
had three digits followed by three digits, we can do
this.
So that's three digits followed by a dash followed by
4 digits.
And again, this is pretty readable I think.
Now what if we wanted 3 digits followed by either
space, dash or dot?
So I'm kind of expanding this to match more characters.
So this will require a character class with square brackets.
So this is match 3 digits match either a space
or a dash or a dot followed by 4 digits.
And you can see the lines that match this.
This has 3 digits followed by a dash.
Same here, 3 digits followed by a space, 3 digits
followed by a dot.
OK, so let's do exercise #2.
So in the home directory is this file words dot
TXT, not the home directory in this directory, see this?
So this is again, I'm in the classes subdirectory and
the words whoops, sorry, add this content.
Notice you've got some uppercase and some lowercase in here
you got some digits and so on.
So back to the slides.
Same thing.
I want you to for each, for each of these
regex's here on the right, tell me which word on
the left matches.
So it's a little bit more complicated, but hopefully you'll
be able to figure that out.
And then the second part is write regular expressions.
So I have two statements here, write regular expressions to
satisfy these.
OK, AI says, do we need to be concerned with
time complexity, CPU intensity when it comes to regular expressions?
Great question.
Yes.
Why?
Because it is possible to write extremely inefficient regular expressions.
And inefficient to me means it uses a lot of
resources on our computer, a lot of CPU, a lot
of memory, slows things down.
Yeah.
So I don't think it's horrible misuse of resources, but
yeah, we can write inefficient regular expressions, which also means
we can write efficient regular expressions.
And we're going to cover that in a later section.
So we'll get to that AI, we'll talk about how
do we write efficient Reg XS.
But in before we do, we get to that or
the next bit.
Let's do this exercise.
I'm going to give you 10 minutes for this one,
so 10 minutes for exercise 2.
And again, I'll be monitoring the questions, so feel free
to ask them.
See you in 10 minutes.
We've got about one more minute, and so in a
minute we'll look at the solution.
Exercise 2.
OK, welcome back.
So let's look at exercise 2.
So we've got and I'm over here in the screen
share.
So we've got this file words dot text.
And the first example here is 0 through 9.
So open square 0 through 9, close square.
And we've seen this example quite a bit.
This is 1 occurrence of a digit character.
So which lines contain one occurrence of a digit character?
And it's the last two again, it's it's confusing a
little because it shows both occurrences of 1 digit.
But remember, since the first match wins, it matches the
one here and the one here.
All right, Next example is cap a dash cap Z
class followed by lower a lower Z.
That means match 1 upper alpha followed by 1 lower
alpha and we see the lines of the file that
have an upper alpha followed by a lower alpha.
All right, the next one is using these predefined character
classes.
Back slash West or word characters.
Back slash S is a space followed by a word.
So this is a word character like NA space and
then a word character like one.
Remember word characters are upper alpha, lower alpha, digit, under
score.
All right, the next one is using POSIX character classes.
Upper means match.
One occurrence of an upper alpha and we see all
the lines that would match.
Then we're adding a carrot right here.
So this means match begin the string followed by 1
occurrence of an upper alpha, and that's all the lines
that begin with upper alphas as you see here.
Now, this carrot is a confusing character in rake X
because it has more than one meaning.
One meaning is begin the string with.
Here it's saying begin the string with an upper alpha.
The other is not in this class.
So if I put the carrot right here, this means
I'm sorry, that was an.
Let me do.
Yeah.
So that means not an upper character.
So that means match one occurrence of a non upper
character.
And if I change this to alpha, which is what
the example has or the exercise has that shows match
one occurrence of a non alpha character, we see those
right there.
So the carrot is confusing.
It means more than one thing.
All right, So Part 2 of exercise 2 right Reg
X is to do the following match lines and words
dot text that have at least three upper alphas in
a row.
So that would be something like this.
So 3 upper alphas is A through Z followed by
A through Z.
Really testing my typing skills here and we see there's
two lines that match 3 upper alphas in a row.
Next, match lines with phone number in phone numbers dot
TEXT have 3 digits followed by a space dash or
period followed by three digits followed by a space dash
or period followed by 4 digits.
Use generic classes that's kind of similar to this one
I did before, except I'm going to add 3 digits
up front here.
Space dash digits, here we go.
All right, I think I'm caught up with questions, so
let me just say this before we go to the
next section.
You see how we have 3 here?
Let's start with this one.
We've got 3 here, and then we've got 3 here,
and then 3 here and then four here.
In other words, we have a quantity of the same
thing, in this case digits.
We have the quantity 4 digits back slash D So
is there a way to represent the quantity or the
number of something?
The answer is yes, quantifiers.
I'm going to go back to my slides and we'll
jump to the next section, which are quantifiers.
Just to kind of pause for a second second and
kind of look at where we are right now.
We are have been talking about the basic rules of
regular expressions, including those most characters match themselves, the dot,
the carrot, the dollar character classes, and then the last
of the basic rules of the quantifiers.
This is kind of going to be the section which
ends the basic stuff, and then we'll move into the
moderately difficult things, and then eventually the advanced stuff.
So let's talk about quantifiers, we'll discuss the syntax, talk
about regular expression rule #2 and we'll embed white space
characters to make our regex's more readable.
This is very important.
As regex's get more complicated, it would be nice to
have them readable, and then we'll do an exercise.
All right, so here's the syntax of quantifiers.
The star character has special meaning.
It means match zero or more of something.
The question is of what the answer is of whatever's
to its left, which we'll talk about.
Plus sign is one or more.
Question mark is 0 or one.
All right, so that first example we've got AB *0.
Sorry, AB star, C star means zero or more of
something of what?
Of what's immediately to its left.
So in English, this regex means match an A followed
by zero or more B's in a row, followed by
AC.
So the the strings that this would match would be
something like AC that's zero B's, ABCABBCABBBC and so on.
So it's an A followed by zero more BS followed
by AC.
The plus means one or more and again it operates
on the thing which is immediately to its left.
So that reads in English and A followed by one
or more BS followed by AC, which includes ABCABBCABBBC and
so on.
And then question mark is 0 or more, sorry, zero
or one.
And again, it operates on the thing immediately to its
left.
So in English, that reads an A followed by zero
or 1B's followed by AC.
So that's an A followed by zero, B's followed by
AC, or an A followed by 1B followed by AC.
That's it.
All right, so star zero or more plus one or
more question mark zero or one.
You can also put numbers within curly braces, so this
first one has a #3 within curly braces.
The open curly 3 closed curly is the quantifier which
operates on the thing immediately to its left, which is
AB.
So in English that reads an A followed by three
BS followed by AC.
So that matches one thing A followed by three BS
followed by AC.
If we have 3 comma, that means three or more.
So this in English reads an A followed by three
or more B's, no maximum followed by AC.
So that's an A followed by three B's followed by
AC4B's followed by AC5B's and so on.
No Max.
And this last example has three comma 5, which means
match 3 through 5 says 3-4 or five B's followed
by AC.
So that's an A followed by three or four or
five B's followed by AC.
Which are these strings here?
All right, remember how we talked about regex's as statements
within quotes, which means not really statements, but we can,
we can kind of think of them as statements.
Same thing.
Quantifiers are kind of like loops because we basically are
in this loop where we're hitting the same stage over
and over again.
So in this case, AB plus C means they followed
by one or more BS followed by AC.
So in the state machine, we transition to an A
and then we would transition to AB, and then we
could just kind of do another B and another B
and another B and another B and eventually transition to
AC for the match.
So it's kind of like a loop in a way.
So let's look at an example.
And by the way, back to my screen share, I
am in the quantifiers subdirectory and I've got this file
words dot TXT here.
We are familiar with it.
I've also got phone numbers dot TXT.
We're familiar with that too.
OK, let's look at these first examples.
This is grab minus cap P.
Just as a reminder, the cap P means we're using
PCRE dialect.
I've got back slash W.
I'll tell you what, let's do this.
I'm going to go back here.
Remember this right here.
This is 3 uppercase alphas in a row.
What I could do, instead of having A-Z within squares
followed by A-Z within squares, is to take that first
one and just add this quantifier.
Exactly the same thing.
So the quantifier there makes I think the regex is
a bit more readable, certainly easier to type.
And that's exactly 3A through Z's.
OK, so let's do the examples here.
On this slide, I've got back slash W3.
That's three occurrences of a word character followed by a
space followed by two occurrences of a digit.
So this three right here operates on the thing immediately
to its left.
That's three word characters right here, TEN, and then followed
by a space character.
That's space and then followed by two occurrences of a
digit, which is 10.
OK, we did this one.
Let's change the three to a four and we see
there's two lines that match 4 occurrences of an upper
alpha.
And of course, if we wanted to, we could replace
A-C with the POSIX A-Z, which is the upper.
OK, so let's go back to.
Let's count out the phone numbers.
There we go.
And let's go back to where we were matching numbers
like this.
And I'm going to do the example in the book,
and we're going to start like this.
I saw the example in the slides, which that can
be rewritten as a back slash D followed by quantifier
3, and then back slash D followed by quantifier 4.
So that's the example on the slide there.
So again, I maintain this is more readable than this.
All right, then the next example is OK, instead of
matching dash, let's match either space dash or dot.
There we go.
So now we match the digits separated by a space
or a dash or a dot.
Now the one that it doesn't pick up is this
1.
So it picks up all of these but not this
one.
And that's because the space dash or dot are not
present in this first string.
So what I can do is I can make this
space dash or dot optional.
Remember the question mark means zero or one occurrences.
So this is 3 digits followed by zero or one
space dash or dot followed by 4 digits.
And now we pick up all the phone numbers.
OK, WZ asks why here is the dash not escaped?
Because the dash has special meaning within the square brackets.
See it here within the square brackets.
That's why I have to escape it here outside the
square brackets.
It's just the dash character, so it has no special
meaning.
This kind of illustrate something a bit confusing about Reg
XS, which is some of the characters have more than
one meaning, so it gets complicated.
So we just have to understand that dash has 2
meanings.
1 is just the dash character unless it's within the
square brackets.
It's the range.
All right, so let's do this final quantifier example.
I'm going to go ahead and show it on the
slide and then I'm going to type it in this
one.
Oh boy.
OK, so here are phone numbers and it's going to
look like this back slash.
I'm going to talk about this after I type it
in, so let me type it in first.
OK, wow.
So what does this mean?
This is complicated, no question about it.
But let me step through and we'll see.
Maybe we can see that we understand this, and the
attempt here is to match every one of these phone
numbers in the entire phone number.
And this regex will do exactly that.
So first we match back slash open print question mark.
Remember, the question mark means zero or one, so that
means match a parenthesis, but it's optional.
So here there's no paren here, there's no paren.
Here there's no paren, but there's a paren right here.
So we're matching that optional paren followed by three digits,
which matches 312312312312 and so on.
This 312 as well, followed by this, which is either
a space dash dot close ( 0 or more.
That means it's either there or it's not.
This could probably be a question mark as well, which
means zero or one.
Let me try that real quick.
Make it a question mark just to confirm.
Yeah.
Oh, it does not match this one because there's two.
That's right.
So there's a ) and a space.
We do need the star here, followed by three digits,
55 fives in these strings, followed by optional space dash
or dot, followed by 4 digits.
And that matches the regex.
So this is clearly the most complicated regex we've seen
this one here.
My hope is you kind of grasp how it's working
and we're going to make this a little bit more
readable.
It's hard to read.
We're going to make it more readable in a minute.
But before we do, we need to talk about regex
rule #2 So I'm going to switch over to over
to slides and talk about regex rule #2 and that
is a quantifiers are greedy.
They're going to consume as much as they can.
So let's look at that.
So here we have Reg XS are really not that
difficult.
That's the string.
Then we've got RE dot star L.
So the RE here in our string can match in
one of two places, either the RE at the front
of Reg XS or the RE at the front of
really.
Then dot star means the star zero or more of
the thing to its left dot, which means any character
but new lines.
This matches zero more of any character but new line
followed by L.
Now the L will match either the first L in
Really or the second L in Really or the L
in difficult.
So the question is where does the RE match and
where does the L match?
And that's best shown by just stepping through this here,
by the way.
It's going to match the RE is going to match
the RE and Reg X's and the L is going
to match the L in difficult.
Let's see how.
So we start at the left of the string.
Left of The Reg X is the next thing.
An R Yep.
Is the next thing an E Yep, dot star.
Now what dot star is going to do is consume
every character that it can.
So it's going to just cruise all the way to
the end of the string.
Why?
Quantifiers are greedy.
They're going to consume as much as they possibly can.
So in this this case, it's going to consume any
character but new line which takes it all the way
to the end of the string.
Now we're looking for an L here we're at the
end of the string.
Is the end of the string an L?
No.
So what it's going to do is it's going to
backtrack.
That's what this means.
It's going to back up looking for an L is
AT&L no, so it backtracks.
Is the L&L yes match this matches.
So because quantifiers are greedy, they're going to consume as
much as they possibly can.
So that's why the RE matches upfront and the L
matches at the end here.
So let's look at this.
We have a BCABCABCABC and then the regex AB dot
star C.
So let's walk through this one again.
So we start at the left of the string, left
of the regex.
We match the A, we match the B.
Now we're at dot star.
Remember, star is greedy, so it consumes as much as
it can.
We're looking for AC, but we're at the end of
the string, so we backtrack.
Then we can match that C and that's the part
of the string which matches.
All right, let's look at this example.
We've got ABC dot star AB dot star C, but
the string is ABCDEFG and so on.
Now we look at this regex.
Does the string match an A followed by AB followed
by zero or more?
Yes.
0 followed by AC, Yes.
So it's going to match and we can see that
with our brains and our eyes.
But regex engine not that smart, so it has to
do this work.
Start at the left.
So is the next character an A, Yes, match next
character B, yes, match dot star consume everything.
Is the next character AC?
No.
So that's the backup.
It's backtracking.
Still not AC, still not AC.
Finally it backs up to here the next character is
AC match.
But that's a lot of work.
Now here we only backed up 10 characters or something
like that.
Imagine backing up a GB of data.
So this can be very inefficient this this quantifiers being
greedy business.
But for us we can see how this is working.
So quantifiers are greedy by default.
We also call this maximal matching.
That means they match as much as they can, and
when necessary the back the regex engine will backtrack.
However, backtracking can be expensive, especially for really long strings.
There is a way to match the opposite, known as
lazy matching.
We'll talk about that later.
There's also a way to turn off backtracking.
We'll talk about that later as well.
Now, before things get even more complicated, let's talk about
embedding white space characters, because this makes our regex is
more readable.
So in the grep command using PCRE, we can embed
white space with this question mark X.
And basically what that means is in the regex spaces
are are just kind of white space meaning it it
they're not actual regex patterns, but they're just a way
to make things more way to spread things out.
So this let me just go to the screen share
real quick and I'll show you what I mean by
this.
All right, so the way to here's our Reg X
that's works but is really hard to read.
If I start The Reg X with question mark X
within parens, I can add spaces in here like this.
And this is just separating the different things from each
other to make things more readable.
You see that?
So it's exactly the same, but these spaces are ignored.
And the purposes is it makes things a bit more
readable because it kind of breaks things into chunks, which
makes things kind of easier to understand.
Yeah, Match an optional open print and three digits, zero
or more.
One of these characters, 3 digits, optional space dasher .4
digits.
So kind of makes things more readable.
And back to the slides, it helps even more in
some programming languages like JavaScript, Python, we can set the
across multi.
We can set The Reg X across multiple lines and
then also embed comments because the comments are pound signed
until the end of the line.
So not only do we have The Reg X with
some spacing in there to make things more readable, we
also have comments to help us understand what it means.
So an optional open print the area code, any number
of separators and so on and so on.
Very, very nice.
All right, I already showed this.
Oh, if we want to include the space character because
the X modifier here means we can embed spaces.
They're just, you know, to make things more readable if
we actually want to match the space character.
One way to do that is to add back slash
X2020 is the hex character hex value of the character
space.
If we put back slash X20, that means match the
space character.
So this Reg X is hello space world.
All right, I showed this example already.
So let's look at Exercise 3.
Same thing for exercise three.
You've got words dot TXT and you've got these 7
Reg XS.
So let's see which words each Reg X matches.
So I'm going to give you once again, I'm going
to give you 10 minutes for this, and we can
start now.
So let's take 10 minutes to do this exercise.
And if you have a couple minutes, take a break
if you need one.
Everyone I I stopped my screen share for a bit
because my virtual box was taking up incredible amount of
memory.
So I'm going to let things calm down a little
bit and then I'll start it up in a bit.
We have about 5 more minutes so I'll give you
a heads up when we have one minute left.
OK, we've got about one more minute.
OK, so this exercise, let's look at these in turn
real quick, and then we'll make sure I've answered all
the questions so far.
I tell you what, I'm going to show the solution
to Exercise 3 when I show the solution to the
next exercise.
So we'll we'll show the solution to Exercise 3 and
4 together.
So let's talk about the next section, inline modifiers, bounding
and alternation.
All right, so we're going to talk about inline modifiers,
what those things are.
We've actually seen one that was that X question mark
X with in parens.
We'll talk about bounding syntax, alternation syntax.
We'll do an exercise and then I'll show the solution
to that exercise and exercise 3.
OK, now these inline modifiers that we're going to talk
about here require PCRE.
So you got to have PCRE for this to work.
The first one is X.
So X we saw was a way for us to
embed white space into our Reg X, which allowed US-led
us to make our Reg X more readable.
And I think it's very important to make our Reg
X's more readable because yeah, I mean, the easier it
is to read, the easier is to understand.
The next modifier is the I modifier.
This does a case insensitive match.
Now remember, by default the matching is case sensitive, but
with the I here does a case insensitive match.
S is what's called single line mode.
It simply does this it it allows dot to match
the new line right?
So by default dot matches any character except new line.
But with the S modifier, dot will match new line
character and then the M is what's called multi line
mode.
This is kind of hard to understand just by talking
about it.
We'll see an example that should illustrate it.
But multi line mode means my string has multiple lines
in a string with multiple lines means there's new lines
within the line within the string, right?
So I've got like hello new line world that's a
two line string.
So if I have a multi line string, the M
modifier changes how care and dollar behave.
Carrot instead of matching the beginning of the string, now
be get matches the beginning of any logical line in
the string.
In dollar, instead of matching the end of the string,
matches the end of any line in the string.
Now because M changes how carat and dollar work, there's
still a way to get to the beginning and end
of the string, and that's back slash cap a for
the beginning, back slash cap Z for the end.
By the way, those will always work whether you use
the M modifier or not.
Now, there are other modifiers that other dialect support, but
these are the PCRE modifiers, so these are the ones
we're going to talk about.
So we've already seen the X modifier, so let's look
at this first example.
Here we're doing a grap minus cap P and notice
we're combining 2 modifiers.
So we have open paren, question mark XI, close paren.
That means we're using the X modifier so we can
embed space characters in The Reg X to make things
more readable.
I means case insensitive or ignore case.
So this is going to match upper or lowercase alphas.
Then we've got the carrot character that says match the
beginning of the string.
And then one or more lowercase alphas means match, you
know, one or more alpha characters all in a row.
But since we're using the I modifier, it matches uppercase
as well.
So this matches because of the I matches lowercase and
uppercase alphas to the end of the string.
So this matches all the lines of the file that
begin with an up any alpha only alphas to the
end of the string.
And we can see the 9 the 10 lines that
match.
Another way of writing the same thing is the second
example.
Notice in the modifiers we've removed the I for ignoring
case, and instead of the lower alpha, we use the
POSIX upper, the POSIX alpha class, which means upper and
lower case.
So these two will basically give us the same result.
All right, Next up, the S operator.
So S modifier.
So here we have open print question XS close for
and that means X means and we can put white
space in there.
S means single line mode.
Now a single line mode means the dot can now
consume new line.
So in this case we say match beginning of the
string followed by hello, dot star, world into the string.
But in this case dot star means zero or more
of any character period.
Any character including the new line character.
This is going to match hello followed by any character
followed by world.
So even if there's new lines in there between the
hello and the world, it's going to match.
And then the M modifier, Notice we have XM here
X so we could put spaces in there.
M means multi line mode.
That means that this string has multiple lines like the
string hello new line, world new line.
You see that example below Hello new line, world new
line.
So that string has new lines in it and if
you were to print that out, it would print hello
on one line and world on another line, right?
So it's a multi line string.
What the M means is that carrot, instead of matching
the beginning of the string, matches the beginning of any
line of the string.
So it would match at the beginning of hello or
it would match at the beginning of the world.
So does this string match carrot world?
Yes, because the carrot matches right before right after the
new line before the West in world.
So here I'm running the echo command.
Notice I'm saying echo open quote, hello new line world,
close quote.
That means that this string that it's echoing out is
hello new line world.
And I'm piping that into the grep minus cap P
which is the PCR E that Z means I'm getting
this from standard in.
So does this string match The Reg X?
And The Reg X here has the XS modifier X
so we can put white space in there S so
the dot matches new line as well.
So does it match begin the string hello?
So hello is at the beginning of the string dot
star which can consume the new line world.
Yes, it matches.
Now we'll pipe to the same string.
Hello new line world into the second grep command, which
is the M modifier, changing how the carrot works.
So does world start one of the lines of the
string?
Yes, and we see world printed out there in red.
OK, pausing to see if there's any questions.
The Next up is bounding.
Now we've seen two bounding characters already.
The carrot bounds to the beginning of the string and
the dollar binds to the end of the string or
right before new line.
So this is what does it mean by bounding?
We can kind of bound or bind or put The
Reg X in a particular location in the string, the
beginning of the string or the end of the string.
This is important because by default Reg X's match anywhere
in the string.
But this is saying I want it to match in
a particular location in the string.
Now the alternatives to Karen Dollar are back slash cap
a back slash cap Z.
OK, question came in.
This link work with anyone?
No, it does not work yet.
WZ.
So it will work after the class.
So that link will be live once the class is
done and I get the history.
So I'm not like keeping a history as we're going.
So after the class is over, I'll grab the history,
upload it and then that link should work.
So give me a few minutes after the class that
to happen.
OK, and finally, the new word bound, the new boundaries.
We're going to talk about our word boundaries.
The word boundaries are back slash lowercase B and back
slash uppercase B.
Back slash lowercase B means match at the beginning or
the end of a word.
Back slash uppercase B match not at the beginning or
end of the word or somewhere that means somewhere in
the middle of the word.
Let's look at some examples.
So here I have this file text dot TXT and
you can see there's 4 lines of text in there.
That first grep I'm doing a grep minus cap P
so we have the PCRE and notice the regex is
back slash BTHE.
So that back slash B means word boundary.
It's to the left of the T.
That means T must begin the word followed by H
followed by E Now if you'll notice, each of the
the four lines has AT followed by H followed by
E in the line.
There's the and then those letters in other letters in
there and those letters in lathe.
But since we're saying find at the beginning of the
word only the lines with the and their match, because
that's where T begins the word.
Now the next example has THE back slash B.
The back slash B is now to the right of
the E, which means E must end the word.
So we're going to match any string that has THE
where E ends the word, and that's the line with
the word dot and the line with the word lathe
that E ends the word there.
Back slash B The back slash B means match T
at the beginning of the word and E at the
end of the word which only matches one line the
OK cool.
So what is this back slash cap B?
Back slash cap B means match not at the beginning.
So the next example is back slash cap BTHE.
That means match THE where T does not begin the
word.
So any word, any line that has THE where T
is not at the beginning is other and lathe.
And then we have the next example has the back
slash B to the right of the E which means
match so that it doesn't end the word.
So we have THE where E does not end the
word like other and there.
And then if we put back slash B at the
left, I'm sorry, back slash capital B at the left
and back slash capital B at the right, then it
matches THE where T does not begin the word and
E does not end the word.
And that's only the word other in this case.
So these two allow us to bound or bind, if
you will, to the to, not to, to the beginning
of a word, end of word or not the beginning
of the word or not the end of word.
OK, so let's look at alteration.
We've kind of seen this way long before very beginning
of the class.
But the vertical bar means either one or the other.
So this Reg X means match an A or anywhere
or AB anywhere.
This rag X matches ONE anywhere or TWO anywhere.
Prince can be used to apply precedence.
So this rag X matches in IN anywhere or outside
anywhere.
And that's because the parens have really low precedence.
So if we want that precedence to be applied to
the in or out, we can wrap it in parens
like this.
So this matches either in or out, followed by side.
So that'll match either inside or outside again.
So the parens are applying precedence around the vertical bar
because the vertical bar has really low precedence.
How about this one?
Here we're applying.
We're using the prints to apply precedence on the vertical
bar.
And it says today is either M Mon or twos,
followed by day.
So it's either Monday or Tuesday.
Of course, today is Thursday, so that's not exactly accurate,
but you can see how that Reg X would work.
So the prints are applying precedence around the vertical bar.
So let's look at the first example here.
Here we have carrot first or second or third dollar.
So because the vertical bar is really low precedence, this
matches either first at the beginning of the string.
So either carrot first, that means first at the beginning
of the string, or second anywhere in the string, or
third dollar that's third at the end of the string,
so it's first at the beginning or second anywhere, or
third at the end.
But in the second example, if we wrap those parens
around the vertical bar, it matches begin the string followed
by either first or second or third followed by the
end of the string.
So we can see how we can use the parens
to apply precedence there.
So let's look at how the regex engine would actually
do this work, and that is it can match an
unexpected part of the string.
So notice here where the string is, it is outside
or inside.
A regex is.
A regex is either in or out all by side.
So this is going to match either the outside here
in the middle of the string or inside at the
end of the string.
The question is which the answer is the first match
wins.
That's Reg X rule #1 But it's interesting that even
though out within this parens vertical bar business happens after
the in in the parens, it still matches 1st.
And again, why the earliest match wins?
And if you think about it, we can we can
kind of represent this vertical bar business as kind of
a branch in the finite state machine.
So in other words, when we get to the in
or out within parens, we're going to branch either to
the top, which is IN or the bottom which is
OUT and then side.
So basically how this is going to work when it
gets processed is where when we get to the O
and outside, it's going to launch us kind of down
into the lower part of this branch where we match
OUT and then we match SIDE.
So we match outside first, even though inside is kind
of you think maybe that would be matched first because
in comes before out.
I know it's kind of a branch at that point.
So let's look at this example here.
Here we have the string 2 is greater than one
right?
So we start at the left of the string, left
of The Reg X.
By the way, it's going to match 2 here.
Why?
Because when we're at the beginning of the string, it's
trying to match the O and one which doesn't match.
So it goes to the next option which sees the
T and two and then the West and then the
O.
So that's why two matches this string instead of the
one at the end of the string.
All right, so let's look at this these examples here.
Now, these examples are going to require us to do
to kind of illustrate this.
I'm using the Perl language to do a substitute.
Just make things more kind of conceivable, if you will.
So here we have this file text dot TXT.
It's got 4567 lines in it.
And then we're going to run Perl minus PE.
That's basically Perl by default uses PCR ES, so we
don't have to do anything special for that.
And the PE is basically going to use the string
provided next as the Perl operator and it's going to
operate on this file text dot text.
That's where it's going to read its data in.
The S operator is what Perl's going to do.
This is the substitute operator.
Much like we saw and said, this says substitute either
one or two with three dashes.
This is going to show us which occurrence of one
or two gets matched in the string.
And we see that for the first 3 lines, it's
the first occurrence of either one or two that matches.
So in the first line it's one second and third
line it's 2.
They get matched and substituted with the dashes.
The fourth line, the first occurrence of either one or
two is 2 at the end of the string.
It gets substituted with dashes.
So then we'll just reverse the two and the one
in the second Pearl command and you see the same
result.
So regardless of the order, the first occurrence is what
gets substituted.
That's the most important thing, regardless of the order.
Now this substitute is a bit different.
It's TW or TWO.
Now the order is important here because basically we're matching
AT followed by AW in both cases.
So it's the left, it's the one to the left
of the vertical bar that actually is going to be
the one that's substituted.
So we see that TW get substituted with a double
equals in the first line, second and third line and
the fourth line.
And if we were to reorder it, instead of TW
getting substituted, it's two get substituted.
That's kind of important when The Reg XS, when The
Reg XS are similar in that regard.
All right.
And then the other examples we saw a moment ago,
same file, we're doing the grap minus cap P And
then we have within the the string, we have match
first at the beginning or second anywhere or third anywhere.
And we can see that the potential matches has the
in the second and third line have second, you know,
not at the beginning of the string because that verb,
that carrot is only attached to the first because the
vertical bar has such lower precedence.
But the second example, if you wrap the parens around
first, second or third, the carrot means match beginning the
string followed by either first or second or third.
And we can see now that only the first, second,
or third at the beginning of the string matches.
All right, let's try exercise 4.
This is a bit more complicated.
And by the way, I didn't mention this when we
started this section, but this is the first bit that
is into the sort of the moderate difficulty of regular
expressions.
So if you're new to regular expressions and you found
this topic that we just talked about a bit complicated,
it's because it is, it's more complicated than the others.
So if you're struggling a little bit, that's fine.
We've got 8 problems here, and I'm going to give
you about, I'm going to give you 12 minutes, which
is going to be until 11:10 here on the East
Coast.
And do as much as you can.
So I don't expect you to finish all these eight
in 12 minutes, but solve as many as you can.
I'll give the answer to say, the first four or
so, and then the rest of them become homework.
So you can solve them at your convenience.
So why don't we take 12 minutes, solve as many
of these as we can.
We'll come back and I'll show the solutions to exercise
3:00 and 4:00.
So I'll see you in about 12 minutes.
Everyone, we've got about two minutes and when we start
up, also the solution to exercise 3 and 4.
OK, let's look at the exercise 3.
Now Exercise 3 is for quantifier.
So I'm in the quantifier subdirectory here and here's my
words dot TXT, very familiar by now.
So the first says, what does A-C caps capital A
through Z2 match in words?
That text is going to match 2 occurrences of uppercase
alphas in a row.
So we see 2 here, 2 here, 2 here.
All right, how about this one change this slightly.
This is going to be lower alpha followed by 1
occurrence of a lower alpha followed by two occurrences of
an upper alpha.
We see it matches those twos strings.
All right, let's try this one.
This is open paren A through Z lowercase, capital A
through Z uppercase, yeah, capital uppercase and notice it's within
parens.
And then we have two.
So what this is doing is it's applying two occurrences
to what's within the parentheses here.
So the parens here are applying precedence.
It's applying precedence around a lower alpha followed by an
upper alpha.
So are there 2 occurrences of a lower alpha followed
by an upper alpha?
No, unfortunately.
So nothing matches.
All right.
How about this one then?
This is A-Z plus.
That's one or more occurrences of an upper alpha.
And so notice one occurrence matches here, and then four
occurrences matches here.
All right, so let's do a little bit more complicated.
This one is A-Z lowercase or uppercase plus followed by
a space character and then one or more digits.
So notice this matches either an upper or a lowercase
A1 or more times.
So this matches 10 here, 11 here, Space character matches
space right after 10 and space right after 11, and
then one or more digits matches the digits here.
OK, cool.
And we have this one.
This is back slash W plus space back slash W
plus.
So back slash W remember is a word character.
Word characters are alphas digits under score one or more
time which matches 1011 and then match a space character
matches the space here and the space here.
And then one or more word characters.
Remember alphas digits under score match these digits here.
And then the next one, we're going to use the
X modifier, which is super helpful in writing Reg X
as we can read.
So instead, instead of back slash S, we're going to
say back slash X20 question mark.
This means that because we have the X here, spaces
are not considered part of The Reg X anymore.
They make make things more readable.
So if we actually want to match a space character,
one way to do so is to say back slash
X20 that's the hex character 20, which happens to be
the space character zero or one times.
And so let's see which things match.
Now we have everything matches.
Why?
Because since this is optional means it's there or not
to match.
All we need is one word character here and one
word character here.
So if we have two word characters, we're going to
match.
But since things are greedy, it's going to it's going
to consume the whole string.
All right, Exercise 3 Part 2 Create regex to do
the following.
So let me just cut this file out again.
Oh, I don't have a line in this file with
three digits that begin and end string.
No.
So let me just modify my words dot text.
So I've got 3 digits and then three more digits.
So it's 3 digits at the begin and three digits
at the end.
Then we have lines that begin with three digits, have
two lowercase alphas in a row somewhere, and end with
three lowercase alphas.
There we go.
And then #3 says lines that begin and end with
more than one digit and have non digits in between.
This can be any non digit thing.
And then begin and end with more than one digit.
So let's give several digits here.
All right, so that's my test data.
So the first is lines that begin and end with
three digits.
So I'm going to say grab minus cap P I'm
going to do my X modifier to make things more
readable, readable.
Begin the string with three digits.
I can have anything at all.
Then three more digits at the end of the string,
and notice it matches these two because this one starts
with three, ends with three, this one starts with three,
ends with three right there, and the dot star consumes
everything in between.
All right, lines that begin with three digits have two
lowercase somewhere in with three lowercase.
It'll look like this begins with three digits.
Got that?
Then we're going to have two let's see, two lowercase
alphas vowels in a row.
What's a vowel?
AEIOU and I didn't make that a vowel.
Hold on, these need to be vowels.
So there we go, and it's two lowercase vowels.
Oh boy, there we go.
So that's three digits.
Lowercase vowels end in lowercase alphas.
OK, that'll work.
So I've got a lowercase A2 times and then end
with three lowercase characters.
All right, so let's look at this a little at
a time here.
So we have begin the string with three digits.
Got that?
And then it says somewhere later are two lower case
alphas.
So the somewhere later is handled by this dot star.
So the dot star says we can have anything in
between the digits and the alphas.
I just have a single space here, but I could
have had any characters at all.
And then I end with three lower alphas.
So again, I have to put this dot star placeholder
to match anything in between and then we've got 3
lowercase alphas there.
So that was number 2.
So exercise three-part 3 is lines that begin and end
with more than one digit and that have non digits
in the in between.
Use generic classes.
So here we go beginning in with more than one
digit.
So what is more than one digit?
Back slash D plus that means one or more and
then have non digits in between.
That's back slash uppercase D non digits one or more
and in with three end with that and that have
two, let's see, beginning in with more than one digit
and have non digits in between.
So it has to end in more than one digit.
And there we have it.
So we have more than one digit in with more
than one digit, non digits in between.
And this line matches as well.
OK, cool.
So that's exercise three.
I'll pause for a second, see if there's any questions
about that exercise.
And if not, I will jump to exercise 4.
So I'm just gonna do the first four of these,
let's say.
So what I'm gonna do is create another file, let's
call it words two dot TXT.
I'm just gonna have some test data for these exercise
4 problems.
Lines that contain hello in upper or lowercase.
So this has hello in lowercase, this one has it
in uppercase, and let's do one with mixcase.
OK #2 words that begin with two uppercase letters.
This line does match, so notice it's a word is
beginning with two uppercase letters.
Then we have words that end with either U or
Z.
So how about do I don't know through and oz?
So that's a lot.
That's a word that ends with U or Z and
#4 words that begin and end with two vowels.
One word is area, another is wow, that doesn't begin
and end with two vowels.
I'll just make this up.
We'll spell it like this.
So that's the word that begins and ends with two
vowels.
OK, so there's my test data.
So #1 lines that contain hello and uppercase.
This one's kind of easy because I can use my
I operator and justice match hello somewhere in the line,
and we see those lines match.
OK, so the nice thing about it is that using
the modifier I means yeah, so and it can match
anywhere at all.
So there we have the three lines that have hello
in various cases, words that end with either U or
Z.
So this one's going to use the word boundary.
So I'm going to say either U or Z at
the end of the word.
So this creates the character class.
So it's either U or Z, and this means at
the end of the word.
And you can see those two match words that begin
and end with two vowels.
This one's a little bit harder.
Vowels a EIOU, that's a vowel.
So I want a word that begins with oops, 2
vowels, then followed by any number of word characters and
then ends with two vowels and at the end of
the word.
And you can see that matches there.
OK, so that was the first four.
Did I do all four?
Oh, I skipped one.
Sorry I skipped #2 words that begin with two uppercase
letters.
Probably see that this one will be pretty easy given
all that we've done so this is begins with two
uppercase alphas.
I don't want the X the I modifier because that
ignores case There we go that begins with two uppercase
alphas.
OK so that's the first four of exercise 4.
I'm going to jump back to my screen.
My slides pause for a moment if there's any questions.
Talked about a lot so far.
So OK, let's talk about capturing here in we begin
with the advanced topics.
I would say.
So if you're new to Reg X's up to this
point, hopefully you've been following along pretty well.
Now we're getting into some advanced features that are going
to be difficult for you.
If you're here in this class and you know a
bit about regular expressions here we're going to be beginning
features that perhaps you don't know about.
So the first is capturing.
So we're going to talk about the syntax will match
recurring text and replace text and turn the capturing off
and then introducing the exercise.
So how does capturing work?
It works with parens.
I'm going to talk about it here, but it won't
mean anything until we look at an example.
But when we use parenthesis and Reg X is it,
it causes capturing to occur.
The first set of parens is stored in this thing
called back slash 1, the 2nd and back slash 2,
and the third set of parens and back slash 3,
etcetera.
Why?
Because this is going to allow us to do 2
things, match recurring text where we we're going to use
back slash 1, back slash 2, back slash 3, and
also extract text out.
Now this can be expensive because when you capture, you
have to store stuff in memory.
So if you're capturing a lot of data, like a
large, extremely large string, you got to store that in
memory.
So it can be an expensive task.
Let's look at an example.
OK so we have the regex open print dot close
paren back slash 1.
What?
OK So what is the open print dot close paren
do?
It says match one occurrence of dot which means any
character but new line.
And the prints say capture it and it's captured and
stored where it's stored in back slash 1.
So if we follow with back slash 1 it's basically
a single character followed by itself.
So again, we're matching repeated text here, and it's matching
a character followed by itself, like a a or BB
or 77, etcetera.
If I have two sets of parens, the first set
of parens captures and stores in back slash 1, the
second set in back slash 2.
So each of those parens says capture dot which means
any character with new line store it the first one
in back slash 1, the second in back slash 2
and then we follow with back slash 1, back slash
2.
So this would match like ABAB or XY XY7878.
So we could have just matched 2 dot characters and
followed by back slash 1.
But wanted to illustrate the two sets of parens.
Now in this case, we're matching a character storing in
a back slash 1 followed by a second character storing
that in back slash 2, followed by back slash 2
followed by back slash 1.
So it looks kind of like this.
So the character matched it in at the beginning is
the last, the 4th character, and the second character which
is captured is third character as well.
So that's like a BBAXYYX.
So let's look at some something more realistic.
So this rag X will match a string with the
repeated word.
So we're using the X modifier and we've got back
slash B open print around back slash W plus close
print.
So back slash W plus which is one or more
word characters is in the parens, which means it's captured.
And then we match the end of the string.
So match beginning of the string one or more word
characters into the string in any number of any characters.
And then we match word boundary the very same character
of same word we matched for and then a word.
So basically this matches any string with the same word
more than one time, like a string that has the
later that we'll see an example of this in a
minute.
And then this matches.
This wraps the back slash W plus in parens.
So it says match back slash W plus from the
beginning of the word and then a space character and
then the same word that so it ends the word.
So this matches the same word twice, like the space
the.
All right, let's look at some examples.
I'm going to go back to my screen share here.
I'm in the capturing subdirectory here, so if I cut
out text dot text, there it is.
So 1st I'm going to show match one occurrence of
a character followed by itself.
So notice it matches L followed by LO followed by
OS followed by S So this is what captures the
character, this is what remembers it.
So if I modify this and say match a character,
a second character, then the second character, then the first
matches IS all by si.
Hey, let's try this Reg X take a little bit
to type in here.
This is back slash B.
This is on the slide on page 210 back slash
B, back slash W plus back slash B dot star
back slash BX/1 back slash B.
Now the first thing I see is this is hard
to read, so I'm going to add the X modifier
in here just to make things more readable.
OK, so this matches a word alpha digits under score
that begins and ends.
So this is going to match a particular word and
we're going to match it again later so that it
begins and ends.
So this should match any string with the same word
twice.
We've got this here and other word this at the
highlighted location, and then the word this at that highlighted
location.
Here we have.
This example has here at the beginning and here later.
This example has the and then later the.
OK, so let's do that last example which looks like
this.
I want to match the same word such that it's
twice in succession.
That's the space that matches.
OK, back to my back to the slides.
OK so the capturing can also be do used to
do a replacement text text replacement.
In order to illustrate this, I have to use said
because crap is not going to allow us to do
this, and the the example we see here is using
the said minus cap E said out-of-the-box, so to speak,
is BRE dialect.
It does support the ERE dialect if I use the
minus cap E mainline option, which I've done here.
There is no PCRE support for said, unfortunately.
But anyway, this is this said says substitute night with
day.
And you can see that when we echo tonight into
that tonight becomes today.
So just to show how said works here we have
an example where we're going to substitute a digit character
with the character Z.
So if I E123 into that, I get Z23.
Only the first occurrence of a digit is replaced.
But if I add this G modifier at the right
hand side of the substitute, you can see all digits
becomes these.
OK, so that's just a simple example of said let's
use capturing.
Now unfortunately in order to use capturing was said we
have to escape the parens, so it makes things a
little bit more difficult to read.
But this says substitute a dot within a set of
parens followed by a dot within a set of parens
that matches 2 characters and then substitute them with the
second followed by the 1st.
So if I E123 into that, the result is 213,
so the one and the two are swapped.
Now if I use said minus cap E, which is
the enhanced Reg XS, I don't need to escape.
So that's much much more readable.
Produces the same result.
Now let's take that example where we had two words
in a row, the same word twice in a row,
and replace that with a single occurrence of the word.
So if I echo the space the into this said,
it says match one or more word characters in parens.
That's going to match the in a space and then
the same word the.
Simply substitute it with a single occurrence of the.
So this is a common thing, editors or word processors
or what have you used to catch 2 words in
a row if you're dealing with text files.
I've done that, by the way, and yeah, a little
embarrassing, but it happens.
OK, Now the parentheses capture, right?
And capturing can be expensive because we're using memory and
so on.
We can turn that off using the question mark colon.
So in this case, let's look at this substitute.
We're substituting either one or two.
Now notice the prints here are going to be used
simply for precedence around the vertical bar.
All right, So it works.
So it's like we're going to match either one or
two and then a space and then one, one or
more word characters.
We wrap those in parens and that's the one we're
interested in capturing.
So we're going to substitute that one, one or two
space, some word with just the word.
So those we have to use back slash 2 because
we want was matched in the second set of parens.
So again, the first set of friends, just applying precedents
have nothing to do with capturing.
So what we can do is turn off the capturing
by adding this question mark colon right here after the
open parenthesis.
This turns off the capturing.
Don't waste resources.
So later we use back slash 1 because that is
the first set of friends that's actually doing the capture.
Let's look at this example.
So we're using the X modifier, so we have the
spaces in there to make things more readable.
Then we have a set of parenthesis that is simply
applying precedence.
Notice that the question mark colon turns off the capturing
for this OR business, and the OR is Http://followed by
an optional S So that's going to be HTTP or
HTPS or FTP.
So these are the different options in, you know, preceding
a URL.
And then we match a colon followed by back slash
slash which is the slash character, then the slash character.
And then we're going to match something and remember it
this time this is anything but the slash one or
more times.
So back slash one in this case is going to
be matched here, anything but the slash which for example
might match www.example.com.
And then we're going to match zero or more zero
or one occurrence of slash followed by anything which might
match slash test slash 1/2 dot HTML or something like
that.
So again, we didn't need to capture HTTP, HTTPS or
FTP.
We wanted the other stuff.
So we turned off capturing and we'll see later that
the captured content can be used after the regular expression
is completed.
That requires a programming language like JavaScript or Python.
So we'll show some examples of that in a little
while.
So this brings us to an exercise.
So the exercises are now becoming more difficult.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going
to introduce the exercise here, give you about 10 minutes
to work on it, knowing there's you'll, you know, you
won't do much in 10 minutes.
That's OK.
And then I'll just stop you and we'll go on.
I won't solve the answers to these exercises.
Solutions are in the back of the PDF.
So I'm going to basically let you work on these
at your convenience, whatever is best for your schedule and
but I'll introduce the exercises and then you can get
started.
So it says match a string that starts with an
upper alpha and has that character later in the string.
So this example my name is Mark.
Notice it starts with a capital M and later we
see a capital M in front of the word #2.
Match a string that has two occurrences of a word
where that word ends the string.
So we saw an example earlier of two occurrences of
a word.
Just make sure that second occurrence ends the string.
So the Acme Corporation is changing its name to Acme
Coyote.
Write a regular expression to change all occurrences of Acme
to Acme Coyote and lowercase Acme to lowercase Acme.
And it says some editors say there should be only
one space character after a sentence or after a period
at the end of the sentence.
So write a Reg X, substitute two or more spaces
after a period followed by an upper alpha with a
single space.
These are difficult, but I'll give you 10 minutes.
I'm going to come over to the screen share and
start my timer.
Start this.
OK, so I'll see you in 10 minutes.
Feel free to drop any questions in the chat.
All right, we've got about two minutes, 2 minutes.
We'll talk about the next topic, lazy quantifiers.
All right, everyone, welcome back.
So as I mentioned, I'm not going to show any
solution to Exercise 5 or any of the other solutions
as we go forward.
So they're basically for you to do at your convenience.
I want to call it homework.
That's usually not a good term, but just do it
whenever you want.
But we're going to go on the lazy quantifier.
So this is another advanced topic.
Remember we talked about quantifiers being greasy greed, excuse me,
greedy.
The we can turn that greediness off, which makes what
we call lazy quantifiers.
We're going to talk about the syntax.
I'll introduce an exercise, make sure I answer all the
questions so the match minimally.
That means lazy.
We follow the quantifier with a question mark.
It's kind of a weird syntax, that's what we do.
So star question mark being zero or more, but match
minimally or match as few as possible.
And again, the quantifier operates on what's immediately to its
left.
This is going to match A followed by zero or
more B's minimally followed by AC.
Plus is one or more, one or more minimally plus
question mark.
So the plus question mark here is operating once again
on B.
So that's an A followed by one or more B's,
minimally followed by AC.
And then strangely, question mark.
Question mark is actually syntactically correct.
It means zero or more.
That's the first question mark.
Sorry.
Zero or one first question mark minimally, that's the second
question.
The numbers within curly braces also work, so 3 occurrences
minimally operates on B.
Now it's kind of weird.
Exactly 3 minimally, Well, that would be exactly 3, so
it really doesn't make sense, but it's provided syntactically as
an option.
3 comma means three or more minimally.
That's the question mark.
And then finally, 3 comma 5 means 335 minimally.
So let's look at some examples here.
I'm going to show these examples in the screen share.
So I'm going back over here to the screen share.
By the way, I'm back to the quantifier subdirectory.
So I'm going to do this.
I'm going to tail -20 Macbeth dot TXT.
So there's a file Macbeth dash act one dot text.
This is the first act of Macbeth.
And if I just tail it out, there's the end
of the first act, just some text, the text file
of the Shakespeare play.
So I'm going to take that and I'm going to
pipe that into grep minus cap P and then it's
going to be question mark XI, which are the XI
can include spaces.
I ignore case and I have a dot star D
that's my Reg XA dot star D Now remember that
the star by default is greedy.
So it's going to match from the first A to
the last D.
See that's it's matching first a last D down here,
first A to the last D and so on.
Now if I turn, I can turn that off by
adding a question mark right here.
So now I'm matching dot star minimally.
That means first A to the first D, not the
last D the first D Here's the first A to
the first D it's the only D.
Here's the first day to the first D, and so
on.
So you can see the difference without the question mark,
it consumed the star.
Consumes everything it can with the question mark, consumes only
what it needs to until it finds that character.
Let's try this again, but this time with this Reg
XA Val anything, a vowel.
So here is a Val EIOU dot star anything.
Oops, right character there dot star and then a vowel
and notice it's from the first vowel to the last
vowel, first vowel to the last vowel.
But if I change the modifier, I add the question
mark to the quantifier, you can see it's from the
first vowel to the next vowel, first file to the
next file and so on.
So that's lazy quantifiers turning off the greediness that is
the default.
I'm watching in the chat AI has talking about different
browsers.
Thanks for sharing that AI.
That's for anyone who needs that information.
All right, so let's go back to the screen.
Share here.
Exercise six are the exercises for lazy quantifiers.
I'm just going to say again, do this at your
convenience.
Number one.
Match a string with two integers separated by a space.
Match all of the digits of the first integer with
the integers with the greedy match.
Only match the 1st digit of the second integer.
Group with a lazy match.
Change the above Reg X so both quantifiers are lazy.
What happens #3 use a lazy quantifier to match the
first quoted string.
The line contains more than one quote with double quotes.
Say that.
What am I talking about?
Text.
Nope.
OK, Eli there Actually the there is not a file
with this line.
So basically what this means is that's the first quota
string.
So you'll in your test data you'll have a string
that has a quoted string, which is a double quote
to a double quote and then another quoted string double
quote to double quote.
Use a lazy quantifier to match the last quoted string
and then match a comma followed later by a comma
using a possessive point.
We haven't talked about possessive yet, so forget about #5
about that one yet.
OK, let's talk about.
Look arounds other questions.
Look.
So now we're entering super advanced Reg XS.
So the look around concept is really very advanced and
the look arounds have this strange syntax which is like
open print question equals.
So let's talk about how these work and show a
couple of examples.
So the look arounds are 0 assertions.
That means they don't actually consume any characters, and they
match characters and then give them back, which means they
don't consume them.
And you probably wonder what does that mean?
We'll see with the examples what that means.
And it only determines a match or not a match.
That's it.
So let's look at look aheads, which we have.
Positive look ahead means this thing must be next.
Negative look ahead, which means this thing cannot be next.
So look ahead example.
All right, we've got this string ABCD, and then we've
got this regex AB followed by and this is a
look at.
This means the next character must be C right now,
if we look at our string, we say, yeah, we've
got an A followed by AB.
The next character must be C It's there.
So this is going to match.
Let's watch.
So we start the left of the string, left of
The Reg X.
You match that A, we match that B.
Now is the next character AC.
It sure is match, but notice it is not consumed.
What I mean by consumed is it's not a taken
from the part of the string that match.
So the only part of the string that match was
the AB.
And then we look ahead, we say C's got to
be there, but we're not going to consume that C
And one of the by the kind of side effects
of that is that the C will be available later
to be consumed.
See that in a minute?
Let's look at this example slightly different.
This says match an A and then AB.
Sure enough.
And then it says the next character must be a
lowercase D is the next character AD No.
All right, let's try this example.
This is back slash D plus.
And then it says the next thing.
So it's one or more digits.
And it says the next character must be a vowel.
Let's try this.
Start at the left of the string, left of The
Reg X.
We have one or more digits.
Yep.
Assume those.
Is the next character a Val?
Yes, but don't consume it.
We have a match.
In this case, we have the same Reg XA different
string.
Consume those digits, and then is the next character a
lowercase Val?
Nope, fail.
All right, now we're going to do what's called a
negative.
OK, that means what follows cannot be something.
So here we have the string abcd percent character.
Let's see if we can match this Reg X.
So first we start the left of the string, left
of The Reg X.
The Reg X says match 4 lowercase alphas.
Got those?
That's just ABCD.
Then it says is the next thing not a digit?
Yes, the next thing is not a digit, but that
next thing is not consumed, so it's still available to
be matched.
All right, let's look at this simple same Reg X
different string will consume those first lowercase alphas.
Now, is the next thing a non digit?
No, the next thing is a digit.
Fail 7 is not non digit.
All right, this is all well and good.
Let's do an exam real kind of a real ish
example.
I say real ish because in in principle this is
a good thing to look at, but in the way
it's implemented is not so great and I'll tell you
why.
So first is we're going to match a password.
Now our password requirements are as follows.
It can only be 6 to 8 characters, has to
be 6, no more than 8, can only be alphas
or digits, must have at least one digit, must have
at least one uppercase alpha.
Now my suggestion is this is not a strong enough
password, but for this example, it's going to work.
To make it more you know better password, we change
the requirements.
We're going to stick with these requirements for this example.
So 6 to 8 characters alphas or digits must have
a digit must have an uppercase alpha.
So let's start with 6 to 8 characters alphas or
digits.
So here my Reg X is using the X modifier
says begin the string followed by and then we're going
to look ahead.
We're going to say do we have between 6:00 and
8:00 where I'm going to call them word characters because
for simplification, all the word includes under score and let
that slide for a minute.
So this is look ahead.
Are there 6 to 8 word characters?
If so, that's satisfied.
Now when we look ahead 6 to 8 characters, they're
not acting and we see them.
We're not actually going to consume them.
So those 6 to 8 characters still remain to be
matched.
Then we say OK, look ahead.
Do we see any character followed by a digit?
So now we know there's six to eight word characters.
We're saying, is there a digit out there somewhere?
If there's a digit out there somewhere, this matches, but
it doesn't consume the text, so it's still available for
the next part, which is, is there an uppercase alpha
out there?
If so, let's consume those 6-8 characters and we'll end.
Now, looking for the 6-8 characters at the beginning and
then looking at the end really doesn't make much sense.
So let's remove those from the beginning.
Here's our answer.
So it says look out there and make sure I
have a digit.
Look out there and make sure I have an uppercase
alpha.
Neither of those, since we're looking ahead, neither of them
actually consume the characters.
Then let's consume the 6-8 characters and we're done.
That's a match.
I think about this, if we weren't using a regular
expression, we would have to do some sort of a
write some sort of a program that would scan all
the characters, do comparisons and so on and so on.
It'd be a lot of work.
But for us, it's one Reg X and we're done.
We also have look behind, so there's positive look behind.
That means this thing must be there negative look behinds.
It cannot be there to the left.
So this says match begin the string zero or more
word characters.
And the thing we look behind us, it must be
AB.
So let's try this.
So at the beginning of the string, we're going to
consume all those word characters all the way across.
Now we're looking to where is the left thing?
Is the thing to our left to be?
No.
So since we consume this with the quantifier, we can
backtrack.
Is the left thing now be be?
No.
Is it now AB?
Yes.
So the thing to my left is AB match.
This is confirming that what's to our left?
It's already been consumed.
Is something All right, let's take all these.
Look ahead, look behind examples and do something real.
What we're going to do is comify an integer.
I don't know if comify is a word.
We're going to take an integer, which is a string
of digits and put commas in the appropriate place.
Now, this example I took from the Mastering Regular Expressions
book, and I mentioned at the beginning, this is an
excellent book.
I highly recommend you get this book.
Let's see if we can do this.
So let's we're going to take a number like 123-456-7890
and add commas to it.
So our first pass says OK, match 1 digit and
remember it in back slash 1.
Then match 3 digits, remember it in back slash 2.
Substitute it with back slash 1, comma back slash 2
and you can see that it kind it adds commas.
Doesn't work correctly, but you can kind of see it's
a start.
Let's add this positive look behind.
So this is saying to my left must be a
digit.
Then I'll match 3 digits.
And since the thing to the left is not consumed,
it's not stored in anything.
Nothing happens with it.
So back slash 1 is the 3 digits in parens.
So I'll substitute that with a comma followed by those
3 digits.
And you can see it takes our number and it
you know, it's much closer.
It's getting there.
This is by using that positive look behind.
All right, so let's let's make this work for real.
All right, so this we've added here what's in red.
We've got this positive look ahead.
That's what the question mark is this.
OK, So what?
What must follow is one or more occurrences of three
digits not followed by a digit.
That mean that's basically going to grab the last three
digits and then it must, those last three digits must
be preceded by a digit.
And we're going to separate, we're going to substitute that
with simply a comma.
Why?
Because neither of those actually consumes and you can see
that this does the right thing it to comify this
integer.
So probably are now saying, wow, he didn't mention this
as advanced.
So that's the power of regular expressions is to be
able to use a regular expression to do something one
would have to do programmatically otherwise.
All right, couple of exercises #1 use positive look ahead,
match the string expression.
The matched text only includes the express portion of that
word.
And using a positive look behind writer's substitution to convert
sort of Jason to more sort of Jason.
See the difference with the double quotes there.
All right, so let's start the, I'm just going to
jump right into the practical, efficient and readable regular expressions.
This section, we're going to talk about practical regular expressions
that solve real problems, efficient regular expressions that write faster.
Reg X is, this refers back to the question we
had at the beginning of the class, which is can
we write inefficient?
Reg X is, yes.
Let's talk about how to write more efficiently, and then
we'll talk about writing or readable regular expressions using something
called subroutines.
Subroutines, there's in quotes, not exactly subroutines.
It's more like macros.
All right, let's start with solving real problems.
We're going to match an international phone number, then we're
going to match a valid date, and then we're going
to match an e-mail address.
These examples come from the O'Reilly Book Regular Expressions Cookbook.
This is a really great book.
It's a cookbook because it has examples on how to
do things, much like a cookbook you use in the
kitchen.
It's like, I want to create a regex to do
this.
You look in the cookbook, find the recipe, and you
see the regex and you apply it to your thing.
So this one is matching an international phone number.
So what is an international phone number?
It's a plus sign.
Must be begin with a plus followed by between 6
and 15 digits.
Must end in a digit.
And optional spaces like plus one space 5312, space 555
space 1-2, that's a international phone.
So this Reg X will do this and not notice
I'm using the X modifier.
Adding in some comments so we can read this better.
So the first part of The Reg X is the
carrot.
That means begin the string.
Then we have we want to start the string with
a plus sign character.
But since plus has special meaning, remember it's quantifier, we
have to escape it.
Now we're matching the plus character.
Then we're going to group without capturing matching a digit
followed by an optional space.
We're going to do that between 5 and 14 times.
So this is going to match between 5 and 14
digits spaces optional anywhere in there.
Then we must be a digit, so we match either
the 6th to the 15th digit there.
And then we end the string so that regex can
be used to match international phone numbers.
All right, the next practical Reg X also taken from
the Regular Expressions cookbook because to match validates in these
formats, so MDYYMDYYY and so on.
So single digit months, single digit days, 2 or 4
digit years, double digit months, double digit days, etcetera.
All right, so I'm using the X modifier so I
can span this across multiple lines.
The first set of parens is applying precedents around the
OR.
Here the vertical bar and the bit right before the
vertical bar is going to match either the month followed
by the day in a single digit, or the month
followed by the day in a double.
Double digits, 2 digits.
So here we're matching A1 followed by either 01 or
two or an optional 0 followed by one through 9.
So this is going to match 1011 or 12 or
one through 9 or 01 through 09.
This will catch the double digit months or the single
digit months.
And then we have back slash, vertical bar match back
slash slash matches the slashed.
And then we're going to match 3 followed by zero
or one that's 30 or 31 or one or two
followed by zero through 9, which is 10 through 29
or an optional 0 followed by one through 9.
So that's going to pick up the days in either
single or double digits.
Now this won't make sense for a date like 2/31,
not 31 days in February, but it'll fit this format.
And we have the day or month, the day followed
by months.
This is basically flipping a month slash day-to-day slash month.
And all we're doing here is moving the thing to
the right of the slash to the left and from
the left of the slash to the right.
And then we'll match slash followed by either 2 digits
for the year or 4 digits.
So we have the first bit says match 2 occurrences
of a digit.
The question mark means optional, it's either there or not
there, followed by two of the two occurrences of a
digit.
So I'll match 2 digits for the year or 4
digits.
And again, not validating that the number is a correct
year, It's just matching.
Our last practical example is matching an e-mail address.
Again, this is taken from the cookbook.
Let's so matching user@example.com.
There's a real simple way of doing that.
The first example says, match one or more non space
characters, the at symbol, one or more non space characters.
That'll match user@example.com.
It'll match a lot of other things too.
It'll match that.
e-mail addresses can have a dash, so we'll add the
ability to match dash character.
You can see that our Reg X is becoming more
complicated.
The last example here is no leading or trailing or
consecutive dots.
So we can't end with more than we have two
dots.
We can't have the dot at the end becoming more
complicated now.
The first example here will catch 99.99% of all e-mail
addresses.
This is a very complex regex.
I'm going to leave this as an exercise to the
reader.
So if you want to, you know, try to understand,
you can do that.
But this RFC 5322 is considered the regex to match
all valid e-mail addresses.
And you can see that is quite a Reg X
right there.
But that's RFC 5322, so if you want, you can
use that in your programs.
All right, so let's move to efficient regular expressions.
The first thing this is writing regular expressions that are
faster consume less memory.
dot * is usually very inefficient.
So if I have dot star somewhere, remember that the
star is going to consume every character that it possibly
can, all the way to the end of the string.
Which means we're going to have to do backtracking, which
is expensive.
We have to store stuff in memory, which is expensive,
and if it's a really long string, it's really expensive.
So use minimal matching.
Now this is usually helpful.
It depends on the string, but it's usually helpful, which
is if you add that question mark there, it does
minimal matching, which means it matches as few characters as
possible.
Basically what we're trying to do here is match a
double quote, a stuff, and then the close double quote.
So trying to match a string basically that's double quoted.
Now the best way to do this is with mutual
exclusion.
So this Reg X says match the double quote character
followed by zero or more occurrences of this class which
is non double quote characters all by double quote.
So basically what this is doing is it's using the
speed of the greedy matching without consuming more characters than
the necessary.
So we're applying the greedy matching star to any character
except the double quote.
So match double quote, anything not double quote to the
second double quote.
Fast, efficient, yeah.
So mutual exclusion is the way to go here.
Another way to make efficient is to use possessive.
This is a possessive quantifier and this doesn't keep track.
So one thing about the star is that, you know,
consumes as many characters as it can, but it has
to keep the them in memory so that if we
have to backtrack, we can backtrack.
If we follow that quantifier, that star quantifier with a
plus.
This turns off backtracking.
Basically this says don't backtrack now, so you're going to
consume all that you can go backtracking.
This is the most efficient way of matching, so we
don't waste memory on the backtracking if the speed of
the greedy and we consume as few characters as possible.
That's.
So the question is, what kind of quantifier do I
use?
The one that produces the correct result?
That's the most important thing.
One that produces the least amount of backtracking because backtracking
is expensive.
It really depends on your data, and the best way
is to experiment.
When you're trying to figure out which the best way
experiment, you can use efficient regular.
Let's talk about efficient regular expressions by eliminating backtracking in
loops.
So again, using the possessive means we won't backtrack, so
that star plus means don't backtrack.
So the second example says match X/W plus one or
more word characters without backtracking.
That's the second plus.
Then we'll match a comma followed by one or more
word characters without backtracking.
Wrap that in parens.
Match that zero or more times without backtracking.
This is basically going to match word, comma, word, comma,
word, comma, word, comma, word.
No backtracking with greedy very efficiently.
Now alternations also backtrack, so quantifiers are not the only
thing that backtracks other alternations.
So best way to deal with these is to refactor
them for better performance.
So you see that ABC or Abd or AB or
ABF, that's expensive.
So we can refactor that by pulling out that AB
from each of those options, put it to the front
of the parens, and now we have AB followed by
either CD.
The other is to consider atomic groups, also known as
possessive groups.
Let's look at those.
All right, here I have a string instinct, and I'm
matching either inside or integer instinct.
Now, to do this match is going to be really
kind of expensive.
So we match the beginning of the string.
Then we fall into the first option.
So we match the I.
Then we match the S, and we match the, excuse
me, the end, then the S Now we're looking for
an I.
That's going to fail.
We start over with the string, go to the next
option, or match an I.
We match it in, and we want to match this
S Nope.
The next character's, the T start over in the string,
go to the next, and then of course we'll match
them.
But there's a lot of backtracking there.
Again, backtracking isn't great.
So what atomic groups allow us to do is turn
off the backtracking for the alternation.
And the atomic groups are created with this question mark
greater than that says no backtracking in this set of
parens around the OR.
And this is only good for mutually exclusive alternatives.
So notice these alternatives are mutually exclusive, either Mun or
twos or Wedness.
This is no chance of having an option here in
one that you have to test another one.
And so because of that, we turn off back tracking,
don't have to keep track.
So we'll start to the left of the string, left
of The Reg X.
We're looking for either MONRTUES, etcetera, which we finally find
way up here.
So we match the T, EU, the E, the S,
no backtracking and we're and then the DAY and we're
done.
If we can turn that backtracking off, that's a good
thing.
OK, next topic, readable regular expressions.
I'm going to say readable.
This case is your mileage may vary you it, you
might think this is readable, you might think it's not
real.
I actually like the feature we're about to talk about,
but some folks might not consider it really hard to
read.
But anyway, we're going to use subroutines.
Now notice subroutines is here in double quotes because it's
really not a subroutine, it's more like a macro.
The macro is defined within this define block.
The macro or a bunch of named things that we
define within these name blocks, and then they're called with
this ampersand name syntax.
Now we'll actually look at an example in a few
minutes when we talk about Python because Python is going
to allow us to do this.
But for now, we'll just kind of talk about it
slides here, but don't worry, we'll get to an example.
So here is the macro.
Notice I'm saying the the modifiers are X, so I
can put white space in here M because this is
a multiple line string.
We're matching I because we want to ignore case.
Then we have this define block where we're defining these
macros and then later using them.
Let's look at the first define block.
Is this open print question mark open print, define closed
print through that second close, right, close print.
There you say, wow, that's that's some weird syntax.
You're right, it's very weird.
That's the syntax decided upon.
So in this define block are the macros that are
being defined.
There's three of them.
Name, there's phone.
Let's look at the definition of name.
So the name definition is within open print question mark
left angle name right, angle through close paren right.
And basically we're defining a name to be one or
more word characters, the space character, one or more word
here.
So very simple definition of a name.
It is simple, but still it works.
And then later we can use that definition with that
syntax blow less than, I'm sorry, open print question mark,
ampersand name.
And then we see the definition of a international phone
number and then a very simple definition of an e-mail
address, and then we use those later.
So this is kind of a way to create macros
for things, especially if these things are reused.
It makes a lot of sense, just like functions in
coding macros in regex's last reused definitions.
Again, we'll see a full example in just a few
minutes.
This brings us to exercise 8.
We're going to write a Reg X match all the
valid URLs and URLs dot TXT.
So I'll go over my screen share here.
This is the practical, efficient, readable section.
And oh there is a.
Hard to say.
There is not URLs dot text.
So create a file called URLs dot text, put some
valid URLs in there and invalid ones.
Then you need to write a regex to match all
the valid ones and try using said to turn each
valid URL into a link with the less than a
href equals business and then the less than slash a
greater than right of regex to match valid Canadian postal
codes.
They're alternating upper alpha and digits.
For example V5K0V1 ACE is optional.
Few alphas are not allowed, so use a negative look
ahead to eliminate these.
An additional invalid alphas for the first position are W&Z's.
You can't use WZ for the very first.
Use sets to substitute all dates in one format to
another #5 writer Reg X with no backtracking to match
a string in this format, which is digits, comma, digits,
comma, digits, any number of digits there, and #6 optional
rewrite #4 using subroutines.
We need to talk about Python to demonstrate this.
We're going to do that next.
Before we do, let's just take one quick 5 minute
break.
Y'all can just kind of get a coffee refill or
whatever you need for 5 minutes, and then we'll talk
about the last section, which is programming in Python And
JavaScript.
We'll be back in 5 minutes.
All right, everyone, let's continue.
We've got 30 minutes of class time, and we're going
to cover the last topic here.
I'm in the slides, which is programming languages.
The topics covered in this section are JavaScript, Python, And
if we have time, said Knock, we will not have
time.
Feel free to look at those at your convenience.
I'm going to introduce the programming language exercise and that'll
be it for the day.
So let's start with JavaScript.
Yes, JavaScript supports regex.
It supports it with a method called the match method.
We're going to talk about matching with match.
We'll also talk about groups.
Now the match matches a regex against the string.
And yes, JavaScript supports the X regex module that supports
PCRE.
So we have this module that supports PCRE, but it's
not kind of delivered or distributed with the normal JavaScript.
So we have to install it.
So the way to install it is to do an
MPM install xreg apps.
I've already got this, I'm pretty sure, but I'm gonna
go ahead and type it MPM install xreg X and
oh, I don't have it installed, so it's fetching it.
So this is going to take a couple minutes.
So while it's installing, I'll go back to my slides
here.
So there's an example here that's going to help us
match and read this.
So I'm going to come back to my shell here.
And as soon as this is done fetching stuff, getting
a whole bunch of things that should install this and
then we'll be able to there goes on.
So let's look at the match dot JS program.
This is the first example.
All right.
So one way to match is to use the STR
dot match method.
This is the match method off of the string object.
Let's say I create a string.
Its value is hello world, hello comma, world exclamation point.
I can take the string variable and call the match
method off of it.
And notice the regex syntax in JavaScript is delimited by
the slashes.
This matches 1 character captures it follows by the captured
characters.
So this will match 2 characters in the row.
So the question is, does hello world have a character
followed by itself?
Sure LL.
So when I run this by the way, I'm showing
what directory I'm in under the programming directory and under
that under the JavaScript directory.
Now to run this, I type node match dot JS
and notice that match one is printed.
Yep, that worked.
So let's try this.
Let's take the string and match it against this Reg
X.
Again.
The string one or more word characters, comma space, one
or more word characters exclamation point at the end of
the string.
Does that match hello, comma space world exclamation point?
Yep, this match 2 is printed here.
Now let's use PCRE.
So the so the STR dot match, it uses ERE
but not PCRE.
So to use PCRE we need this module that you
that we installed here, this library.
And so I'm going to require the library stored in
this object xreg apps pronounce.
And I'm just going to call that objects constructor with
this double quoted string from here to here.
Now the double quoted string, and by the way, this
is the X modifier out here.
Remember the X modifier allows me to use space characters
in the regex.
So this regex has begin the string and then back
slash W plus annoyingly, the back slash must be escaped
with the back slash.
Very annoying, but that's what we have to do.
So do a back slash W which is a word
character.
We have to say back slash back slash W1 or
more word characters.
A comma back slash back slash S creates back slash
S That's a space.
One or more word characters exclamation point at the end
of the string X modifier means we can have all
these spaces and comments.
Also annoyingly this each line must end in a back
slash right before the new line character.
And then we say OK now we'll call the string
match method, but this time pass in this regular expression
object that we create.
So it uses this Reg X and of course it
matches 3.
Now not only can we say SGR dot match regex
object, we can say regex object dot test passing in
the string.
So that's the two ways to use the regex regular
expression object to do matching.
OK, so let's go back to our slides.
You can also do grouping with JavaScript.
JavaScript groups because the match method actually returns an object.
So if we say var result equals SCR dot match
some regex in there, then it'll return back an object
that we can use to pull out information like.
Results of 0 is the part of the string that
matched.
Results of 1 is the first group, that's the first
set of parenthesis.
Results of 2 is the second set of parenthesis.
We can also grab the index for the match begins
and also the entire string.
So let's look at an example.
This is called groups dot JS.
OK the first I'm creating a string here.
Reg XS are awesome and I'm going to take that
string and do a match and the match is back
slash W plus globally.
That means match one or more word characters to match
every occurrence.
It's going to match these three right here going to
match Reg XS match R match awesome.
So when I print the result, let me run this
over here, O groups dot JS.
This is the result here.
So if I look at results of 0, results of
1, results of two, that's the different pieces of the
string which match that regular expression.
I see our console log, this dash line that's right
here.
I'm going to match something different that's using the grouping
here, the parenthesis.
This says match begin this.
I'm sorry, match a space character grouping around word characters
space.
If we're looking for space, word character space, that's right
here space R space.
When I look at the results, here's the result.
I notice it shows part of the string that matched
first group.
That's the thing within parenthesis, the index.
That's the beginning character where the match matched in the
string.
0 based the input string and then any groups which
happened to be undefined because we're using it right here.
So anyway, we'll print results of 0 is space R
space right here.
Results of 1 is R the index the input, and
then we're going to print another dash line.
And then we'll match begin the string followed by one
or more word characters which are remembered.
This should be Reg XS dot star consumes as much
as possible, and then a space which will grab the
last space right here, and then one or more word
characters, which is awesome.
So this matches the whole string.
Groups results of 1 is Reg XS results of two
is pause.
OK, that's JavaScript.
Pause for a second, see if there's any questions.
Nope.
OK, talk about Python.
So Python also supports regular expressions.
I in my experience I would say Python is a
bit more common to use in JavaScript in general and
it has its own syntax and how it handles things.
The one thing about these programming languages implementing or having
regular expressions as features of their language is that they
all have syntax slightly different.
So the syntax for JavaScript is the different is different
from the syntax for Python, which is different, Java, which
is different, Go, which is different from.
So, but the same contact, same concepts will apply, right?
So with Python, we're going to talk about matching with
match and search.
So there's two methods to match.
They're very different.
Talk about the differences.
We'll talk about using groups in Python like we did
with JavaScript, and then we'll talk about a subroutine.
Again, this is more like the macro example.
All right, so first, there are two methods to match
in Python.
There's the match method, and there's the search method.
They're very different.
The match method only matches at the beginning of the
string, so it always assumes that you're matched.
Attempting to match at the beginning of the string search,
however, matches anywhere in the string.
I remember what I said several times in this class
is that by default a regex can match anywhere in
the string.
So the match method here restricts the matching to the
beginning of the string, which to me makes no sense
because matching should be anywhere in the string by default.
That's why I use the search method, not the math
match method.
So I'm going to suggest to you consider not using
match but instead using search.
And in this example we see match hello, matches hello
at the beginning of the string.
We can easily do that by adding the carrot character
to match the beginning of the string.
So everything you can do in match you can do
in search.
So search is recommended over my suggestion.
So for complex Reg XS, we can compile them and
use them as compiled objects to call search.
This will speed up your Reg X matching, especially if
you use the same regular expression to match more than
one times.
You'll have to compile it once.
You can use the modifiers like the X modifier, the
I modifier with this RE dot X and RE dot
I business and you can combine them with the vertical
bars.
So RE dot X vertical bar RE dot I means
I want to use both the X modifier, which allows
me to embed spaces in the regex, and the I
modifier, which does case insensitive match.
Let's look at an example.
So we're now in the Python subdirectory here.
There's 3 examples.
The 1st is search dot π.
All right, I'm going to come over here into this
shell CD into Python.
I'm going to go ahead and run this over here.
All right so in Python, the first thing we must
do is import the module that we want.
Now with the normal Python distribution, that means if you
install Python on a machine, you automatically get the RE
module.
This is the regex module and it but it supports
ERE, not PCRE.
It's only supporting ERE.
Don't worry, we'll we'll get PCRE in just a moment.
All right then.
I'm assigning this string S Python uses the RE module
and then from the RE module I can call the
search method.
And the search method in Python takes 2 arguments.
The first argument is The Reg X and notice it's
within quotes, not slash in quotes.
And then the second argument is the string we're matching
the regex against.
So this is matching the regex RE space module against
the string up here.
So does the string match RE space module?
Sure, right here.
So this should print.
This should return true and print match one.
Now this is showing the search method which is needed
here because this isn't at the beginning of the string.
So if I change this to the match method, notice
that this is expecting R to begin the string followed
by the rest, which is not the case here.
So match to not is correct.
Match to is not printed up here so it does
not match.
So again my suggestion, don't use the match the search
OK, we can also create compile A Reg X with
the RE dot compile method and grab it into a
variable which we can then use the variable to do
the searching and then we simply pass in the string.
So because this variable has The Reg X already compiled,
we simply pass in the string when we're done.
So here's the The Reg X.
Notice we're using first triple quoted string.
The in Python, a triple quoted string allows it to
pass across multiple lines.
We see this going across multiple lines.
The R means it's a raw string, so we don't
have to escape anything.
We don't have to escape these slashes and escape anything
else.
So this is a multi line raw string and then
the X modifier allows us to have spaces in the
rag X.
So this is in the string any number of any
characters match a space followed by a number of word
characters any number of times into the string.
And this does indeed all right.
Talk about back to the slides here.
Grouping.
So text match within grouping parens are available within the
following methods.
m.groups is all a list of all of them.
We can access individual ones with m.groupsof0 is the part
of the string that matched, m.groupsofone is the first group,
so 2 is the second group, and so on.
And this is illustrated in groups Pi, this one.
There it is.
And I'm going to go ahead and run it over
here allrightsoivegotthestringjohn@example.com.
Simple string, just an e-mail address.
Then I'm going to do an RE.
I've imported RE again.
We do an RE dot.
Compile another raw string, triple quoted so it can go
across multiple lines.
Begin the string.
Match one or more word characters, remembering it in a
group.
This is going to match John.
That's the at symbol, which is right here at.
That's another one or more word characters which should match
example.
Match the dot.
Match the dot character.
Another one or more work should Match.com.
So the first group is John.
The second group is example the third group on the
end the string and let's search.
So we do the RE object result of the compile
dot search S in the string and capture that back
in an object.
So now we have this object that is the result
of the search.
We check if the object does not null, then we'll
print match.
Then we'll print that match object that prints this line.
You can see there's some stuff in the object that
gets printed out by default.
Not very useful, but it's there.
m.groupsshows all the groups.
These are the three parts of the string that were
captured.
M subgroup dot of 0 is part of the string
that match which is the whole string right here.
m.group sub one is the first.
The thing in the first set of prints which is
John group sub 2 is the second set of prints
which is the example.
And this last bit right here is going to loop
through loop group in all the groups, printing the group.
And you can see it prints those three pieces of
the string that were captured.
All right, back to the slides.
We got one more example, then we're done.
Subroutines.
Now, remember we talked about these just a few minutes
ago, but we had to wait until we talked about
Python to actually show an example.
So let's look at the example we saw earlier with
the define block macros defined and then used.
And this is in subroutines dot pive.
Now the first thing we see is we have to
import a different module, regex module, which means I have
to install it.
I'm just going to install it real quick here while
we're talking about the code.
There we go.
All right, So, oh, it's already satisfying.
I guess I already installed it anyway, that's how I
would have installed it and I needed it.
And then what I'm going to do over here is
I'm just going to go ahead and run this and
we'll look at what it produces.
There it is.
OK, so first S is a multi line string, 3
lines.
I've got name John Doe, new line, phone +1, etcetera,
new line, email.john@doe.org new line and then the end of
the string.
So it's a three line string and then I'm going
to compile the rag X right here.
This is straight from the example we saw before this
begins, the define block sends it.
Each define has block has a number of definitions.
This is defining the macro name.
This is defining the macro phone.
This define the macro e-mail and we use them down
here ampersand name, ampersand phone, ampersand e-mail.
It's the exact same example we saw before we're compiling
this, the X modifier, we have spaces in here, the
M modifier, treating this as a multi line string.
So carrot, we're treating this up here as a multi
line string.
So carrot matches the beginning of the beginning of each
of these lines, OK, and then dollar matches the end
of each of these lines.
And then I ignores case.
So if we have lowercase A through Z here, we
can have uppercase.
Hey, we compile it does a match.
Yes, it matches.
And here's the object.
So notice that the name is used here, which basically
plugs this Reg X right here, which matches word character
space word character that matches John Space Doe.
This phone business right here replaces this with the macro
we defined up here, which is plus followed by 615
digits matches here.
And then finally we plug in this very simple Greg
X for the e-mail right here, which matches John Doe
it.org.
Great.
All right, well, now what if we wanted to reuse
one of these?
Let's say I come up here.
Not only does John have a phone number, let's call
it his work phone, John has a cell number.
Now what this means is it's very easy to match
the cell.
I just reuse that macro and it matches.
You see that, so the real benefit of having a
macro phone is that I get to reuse it.
That means this.
If I ever change the definition of a phone, I
only have to change it once here.
I don't have to change it twice.
That's the real benefit.
All right, back to the slides.
We don't have time for said knock, so again, it's
your convenience.
I'm going to jump ahead to this side.
Remember these, these were The Reg X as we saw
at the very beginning of the class when I said
Reg XS are complicated.
We've seen all these in this class.
I hope that you understand them to a degree at
least more than you did when the class started.
That was the real goal.
Do you understand more now than when we started?
I hope is that you can say yes.
And with that, I'm going to say thank you for
attending.
If you'll notice on this slide is that's my e-mail
address.
I welcome any emails.
If you have any questions going forward, please feel free
to send me an e-mail, happy to answer them.
The other thing is that soon after we're done here,
I will get the history, all the commands and we'll
paste them, or I should, we'll create that text file,
put it online.
With that, I'm done.
I'm going to turn it back over to Ellen.
Ellen, take it away.
All right.
Thank you, James.
Thank you to everyone who participated in today's course.
Excuse me.
This concludes learning regular expressions with James Lee.
Please take a moment before logging off the fill out
brief course feedback survey.
The course was recorded and we'll be sending you an
e-mail with a link to the recording.
The recording is also available from the course landing page.
Thanks again for attending.
We hope that you've benefited from a course and look
for your participation in future O'Reilly Live courses.
Goodbye everyone.